<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise vpon John 8. 36 concerning Christian libertie The chiefe points whereof were deliuered in a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Nouemb. 6. 1608. By George Dovvname Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Downame, George, d. 1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110210</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845801</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177216</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12497)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177216)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 923:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise vpon John 8. 36 concerning Christian libertie The chiefe points whereof were deliuered in a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Nouemb. 6. 1608. By George Dovvname Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Downame, George, d. 1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 104 p., folded table   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Matthew Lownes, and William Welby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The doctrine of Christian libertie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John VIII, 36 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177216:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177216:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> TREATISE VP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON IOHN 8. 36. CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING CHRISTIAN LIBERTIE. THE CHIEFE POINTS WHERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OF WERE DELIVERED IN A SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, <hi>Nouemb.</hi> 6. 1608. By GEORGE DOVVNAME Doctor <hi>of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>GALATH. 5. 13.</bibl> Brethren, you are called vnto libertie; onely vſe not your libertie as an occaſion to the fleſh, but through charitie ſerue one another.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON, for <hi>Matthew Lownes,</hi> and <hi>William Welby.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:177216:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177216:2"/>
            <p>REVEREND ISSIMO IN CHRISTO PATRI, AC PRAE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVLI CLARISSIMO, DOMINO RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARDO BANCROFT PROVIDENTIA DIVINA ARCHIEPISCOPO CANTVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIENSI, TOTIVS ANGLIAE PRIMATI ET METROPOLITANO, SERENIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIMO REGI IACOBO AB INTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIS CONSILIIS, DOMINO SVO OBSERVANDIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIMO;</p>
            <p>G. D. TRACTATVM HVNC DE LIBERTATE CHRISTIAN O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RVM, AD EORVM FIDEM IN CHRISTO LIBERATORE FIRMANDAM, VITAM SECVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DVM LIBERTATIS SPIRITVM FORMANDAM, CONSCIENTIAS A SPIRITV SERVITVTIS LI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERANDAS, LITES QVE DE ADIAPHORIS SEDANDAS CONSCRIPTVM, LVBENS ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITO QVE VT MECAENATI AC PATRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NO STVDIORVM SVORVM COLEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DISSIMO, IN PERPETVVM SVM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAE OBSERVANTIAE TES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIMONIVM D. D.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <pb facs="tcp:177216:3"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Explication, of the
<list>
                     <item>Context of Coherence. § 1</item>
                     <item>Text: the argument wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Chriſtian libertie. §. 2. which is ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in
<list>
                           <item>Generall: the generall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the
<list>
                                 <item>Definition, and partition, ſhewing what it is, and wherein it doth conſiſt. §. 3.</item>
                                 <item>Explication of other ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as the
<list>
                                       <item>Author or efficient, the Sonne of God. §. 4.</item>
                                       <item>Subiect, the ſonnes of God. §. 5.</item>
                                       <item>Propertie, that it is a true libertie. §. 6.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Speciall, For it is either the libertie of
<list>
                                 <item>Grace, and that either
<list>
                                       <item>Common to all the faithfull: §. 7. as the libertie of sauing grace, either
<list>
                                             <item>Vniting vs to Chriſt, as the libertie of Vocation, which as it is an
<list>
                                                   <item>Immunity, is freedom of our
<list>
                                                         <item>Minds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeruitude of
<list>
                                                               <item>Ignorance.</item>
                                                               <item>Incredulitie.</item>
                                                               <item>Vanitie.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>Hearts, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeruitude of
<list>
                                                               <item>Diſobedience.</item>
                                                               <item>Infidelitie.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>Selues, from the
<list>
                                                               <item>Seruitude of Satan.</item>
                                                               <item>State of damnation. </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>
                                                      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                                                         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                                      </gap> or right, is the dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of
<list>
                                                         <item>Spirit of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</item>
                                                         <item>Faith,</item>
                                                      </list> By which we are made
<list>
                                                         <item>Members of Chriſt.</item>
                                                         <item>Sons of God, and ſo enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to all the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gods children.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list> §. 8.</item>
                                             <item>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Chriſt vnto vs: as the libertie of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſanctification, of which
<list>
                                                   <item>Iointly, that they are not to be condemned. §. 9.</item>
                                                   <item>Seuerally; of the libertie of
<list>
                                                         <item>Iuſtification, which as it is an
<list>
                                                               <item>Impunitie is freedome from the
<list>
                                                                     <item>Guilt of ſinne. §. 10.</item>
                                                                     <item>Law, in reſpect of the
<list>
                                                                           <item>Malediction. §. 11.</item>
                                                                           <item>Exaction of inherent righteouſnes to iuſtification. §. 12.</item>
                                                                        </list>
                                                                     </item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                               <item>Right, we are by it
<list>
                                                                     <item>Iuſtified, and accepted as righteous in Chriſt.</item>
                                                                     <item>Made partakers of the bleſſednes promiſed to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                                                                     </item>
                                                                     <item>Saued in hope.</item>
                                                                     <item>Secured in the queſtion of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification to reſt only on the mercies of God and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt.</item>
                                                                     <item>Indued with theſe priuileges, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of iuſtification, <hi>viz.</hi>
                                                                        <list>
                                                                           <item>Peace with God.</item>
                                                                           <item>Free acceſſe to God.</item>
                                                                           <item>Spirit of adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                                                                           <item>Hope of ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                                                                           <item>Ioy in the holie Ghoſt.</item>
                                                                           <item>Perſeuerance to ſaluation.</item>
                                                                        </list> §. 13.</item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>Sanctification, which as it is an
<list>
                                                               <item>Immunitie, is freedome from the dominion of
<list>
                                                                     <item>Sinne. §. 14.</item>
                                                                     <item>Law. §. 15. <hi>viz.</hi> from the
<list>
                                                                           <item>Irritation thereof.</item>
                                                                           <item>Terror or coaction.</item>
                                                                           <item>Rigor or exactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of perfect obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acceptation of our actions.</item>
                                                                        </list> §. 16.</item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                               <item>Right, therein
<list>
                                                                     <item>We are made partakers of the diuine nature.</item>
                                                                     <item>We haue the
<list>
                                                                           <item>Spirit to be our gouernour.</item>
                                                                           <item>Law, our counſellour.</item>
                                                                        </list>
                                                                     </item>
                                                                     <item>Wee are enabled to ſerue God with willing mindes and cheerefull hearts.</item>
                                                                     <item>Our imperfect obedience is both
<list>
                                                                           <item>Accepted.</item>
                                                                           <item>Rewarded.</item>
                                                                        </list> §. 17.</item>
                                                                  </list>
                                                               </item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Peculiar to the faithfull vnder the Goſpel. The doctrine where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is
<list>
                                             <item>Taught, by expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the
<list>
                                                   <item>Parts, for as it is an
<list>
                                                         <item>Immunity, it is freedom, from
<list>
                                                               <item>The ceremoniall and iudiciall lawes of <hi>Moſes</hi> §. 18.</item>
                                                               <item>Obligation of conſcience in reſpect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things. §. 19.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>Right in regard of the
<list>
                                                               <item>Ordinances of men.</item>
                                                               <item>Creatures of God.</item>
                                                            </list> §. 20.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>Nature thereof, ſhewed by application of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, in three points: <hi>viz.</hi> that it is a libertie
<list>
                                                         <item>Of the ſonnes of God.</item>
                                                         <item>Spirituall, and of the conſcience.</item>
                                                         <item>True, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded libertie, in reſpect of
<list>
                                                               <item>Humane lawes.</item>
                                                               <item>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For there are 4. bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds:
<list>
                                                                     <item>Pietie.</item>
                                                                     <item>Sobrietie.</item>
                                                                     <item>Loial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</item>
                                                                     <item>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. §. 21.</item>
                                                                  </list> Betweene which wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                                                     <desc>•</desc>
                                                                  </gap> there ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict, we are taught what is to bee done. §. 22.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>Maintained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections of
<list>
                                                   <item>Anabaptiſts, who thinke themſelues not bound at all, to humane lawes.</item>
                                                   <item>Papiſts, who thinke that humane lawes do binde the conſcience. §. 23.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Glorie. §. 24.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vſe, to them that haue
<list>
                     <item>Not obtained this libertie.</item>
                     <item>Obtained it: whoſe dutie is to
<list>
                           <item>Stand faſt in it.</item>
                           <item>Be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to
<list>
                                 <item>Auoid the abuſe of it. §. 25.</item>
                                 <item>Vſe it aright, for the
<list>
                                       <item>Sanctification of our liues.</item>
                                       <item>Pacification of our conſiences. §. 26.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:177216:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177216:4"/>
            <head>THE DOCTRINE OF CHRISTIAN LIBERTIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>IOHN 8. 36.</bibl> If therefore the Sonne ſhall make you free, you ſhall be free indeed.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are a concluſion <note place="margin">§. Sect. 1. The context.</note> of the verſes going before. For whereas our Sauiour CHRIST hauing promiſed ſome of the hearers, who, <note n="a" place="margin">Verſ. 30.</note> whiles he was yet ſpeaking of his perſon and office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to beleeue in him, that if they did approue themſelues to be his <note n="b" place="margin">Verſ. 31.</note> true diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, by their perſeuerance and conſtant abiding in his word, they <note n="c" place="margin">Verſ. 32.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould know the truth,</hi> (that is, hee would more fully manifeſt himſelfe vnto them, as he ſpeaketh Ioh. 14. 21.) &amp; this <hi>truth,</hi> (which is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, Ioh. 14. 6.) <hi>ſhould make them free;</hi> the captious <note place="margin">John 14. 6. 22.</note> Iewes (pretending that they vnderſtood him as ſpeaking of a corporall or ciuill libertie) <note n="d" place="margin">Verſ. 33.</note> cauilled at this promiſe, which indeed did not belong vnto them, as if he had offered them great indignitie, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177216:5"/> promiſing them libertie, to preſuppoſe their ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; alleaging that they were alreadie free, and therfore ſcorned his promiſed libertie, which they needed not, being neither ſeruants by nature or birth, for they <hi>were Abrahams ſeed,</hi> nor yet by their fortune or perſonall condition, for they <hi>neuer ſerued any.</hi> Our Sauiour therefore, both to refute their cauill, and alſo to iuſtifie his promiſe, proueth theſe foure things vnto them: 1. That they were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. 2. That they had great need to be made free. 3. That this freedome muſt come by him. 4. That being freed by him, they ſhould be free indeed.</p>
            <p>The firſt he proueth thus: <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. 34.</note> 
               <hi>whoſoeuer committeth ſinne,</hi> that is, in whomſoeuer ſinne raigneth, <hi>he is the ſeruant of ſinne;</hi> but ſuch hee inſinuateth they were, yea ſuch are all men <note n="f" place="margin">Tit. 3. 3.</note> by nature, vntill they be ingrafted into Chriſt by faith, and renued by the holy Ghoſt; and therefore he would haue them to conclude, that, for all their bragges, they were the miſerable ſeruants of ſinne, and conſequentlie the ſlaues of Satan <note n="g" place="margin">1. Joh. 3. 8.</note>, ſubiect to the curſe of the law, and to eternall damnation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they had great need to be made free, he ſheweth both by the inconuenience of their ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; (for being <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. 35.</note> ſeruants, and not ſons, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer now they had a place in the houſe of God, as <hi>Iſmael</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 22. 10.</note> had; yet the time ſhould come, that they ſhould be caſt out;) and alſo by the benefit which ſhould accompanie their freedome, that being made the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of God, they ſhould as heires of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, <hi>abide,</hi> not only to the end of their daies in the Church militant (which is the houſe of God <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 15.</note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:177216:5"/> vpon earth) but alſo for euer in the Church trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, which is Gods <note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 14. 2.</note> houſe in heauen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the faithfull attaine to this freedome by adoption in Chriſt. For, to <hi>ſo</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 1. 12. Gal. 3. 26.</note> 
               <hi>many as receiue him by faith, he hath giuen this libertie or power to be the ſonnes of God.</hi> And, <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 8. 17. Gal. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>if ſonnes, then alſo heires.</hi> This aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is preſuppoſed in this place, as being the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis wherupon this inference is grounded. Thoſe that be the ſonnes of God, abide in the houſe of God for euer; therefore if the Son ſhall make you free, &amp;c. preſuppoſing that men attaine to the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Gods ſonnes, by the benefit of Chriſt, the only begotten Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, as I ſaid, is inferred the fourth thing, which is my text; <hi>If the Sonne therefore ſhall make you free, you ſhall be free indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if he had ſaid: you haue no cauſe to cauill at the promiſe of libertie, which I make to all them which truly beleeue in me. For I tell you vpon my word, which is Amen (that is, true and infallible) that both you, and all men by nature, though the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> (as you are), though liuing (as you do) in the viſible Church of God, are the very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of ſinne; that being ſeruants and not ſonnes, they muſt not looke to inherite <note n="n" place="margin">Galath. 4. 28.</note> with the ſons of the promiſe, or to abide in the houſe for euer; but when the time of ſeparation commeth, they ſhall as <note n="o" place="margin">Matth. 3. 12. 13. 30. 25. 33.</note> chaffe, be ſeuered from the wheate; as tares, from the corne; as goates, from the ſheepe; as <note n="p" place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. Galath. 4. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> from <hi>Iſaak</hi> the ſonne of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Therefore, though your pride will not ſuffer you to ſee and acknowledge thus much: yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177216:6"/> great need haue you to be made free; that of the ſeruants of ſinne, you may become the ſons of God. But you, who are (as all <note n="q" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 3.</note> men by nature are) the children of wrath, cannot poſſiblie be the ſons of God, except you beleeue in me, who am the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Son of God; that I may by the grace of adoption communicate that vnto you, which I my ſelfe am by nature and eternall generation. So ſhall you, of the ſeruants of ſinne, ſons of Satan, and heires of hell and damnation, be made the ſons of God, heires of eternall life, citizens and free deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the kingdome of heauen. Whereas now therefore you are miſerable ſeruants, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your corporall and carnall libertie, whereof you vaunt, which is not a true libertie, but a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie ſeruice of ſin: if you ſhall beleeue in me, and approue your ſelues to be my true diſciples, by abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my words; I, who am the truth, will make you free, not with a counterfeit or imaginary free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſuch as is your libertie, but with a true and ſpirituall freedome, which is the gracious, and the glorious libertie of the ſons of God.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you heard the context, or coherence of theſe words with the former, (whereunto we are referred by this word of inference, <hi>therefore)</hi> wherein diuers things might profitablie be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but that the text calleth me vnto it, as contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning matter of greateſt importance.</p>
            <p>For Chriſtian libertie, which is the argument of <note place="margin">§. Sect. 2. The text. The argument wherof is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie.</note> my text, is, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 14. 16.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good of Chriſtians; which Chriſt our Sauiour, taking vpon him the forme of a ſeruant, hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177216:6"/> with his own moſt precious <note n="s" place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 18.</note> blood; which is the benefit of the Meſſias, whereunto we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 5. 13.</note> Galath. 5. 13. which he hath promiſed as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to his true diſciples <note n="u" place="margin">Iohn 8. 32.</note>, verſe. 32. which as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe came to preach <note n="x" place="margin">Luke 4. 18</note>, Luk. 4 18. ſo doth he ſend vs his Embaſſadours to the ſame end, viz. to preach the Goſpell, which is the <note n="y" place="margin">Iames 1. 25. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>law of libertie,</hi> and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of redemption and freedome by him: that by our Miniſterie <note n="z" place="margin">Act. 26. 18.</note> men may be brought out of ſpirituall bondage, vnto the libertie of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. The conſideration whereof, as it bindeth me with all reuerent care and intention of mind, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of this argument; ſo ought it to moue you to heare the ſame with great diligence and attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the rather, not only becauſe among vs, who profeſſe the Goſpell, many do not know the Chriſtian libertie, and more do abuſe it to their owne perdition; but alſo becauſe the Papiſts are both enemies of the libertie it ſelfe, endeuouring by their Antichriſtian doctrine, to bereaue vs of the chiefe parts thereof, and alſo malicious ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the moſt Chriſtian and comfortable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our Churches concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>But to come to the words of my text, the ſumme <note place="margin">The explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the text</note> and effect whereof is this: that <hi>Christ the Sonne of God, is the author of true libertie, to all thoſe that truly beleeue in him.</hi> For the explication whereof, we are firſt to ſpeake of this libertie in generall, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to deſcend vnto the particulars. In the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <note place="margin">The generall doctrine of Christian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</note> doctrine we are to conſider theſe foure things. 1. What it is, and wherein generally it doth conſiſt. 2. Who is the author of this libertie, which in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177216:7"/> text is expreſſed to be the onely begotten Sonne of God. 3. The ſubiect or the parties on whom this libertie is conferred, which is plainly gathered out of the context or inference of theſe words vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former, to be all the ſonnes of God by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption. 4. The generall property of this liberty, that it is not a counterfait or imaginary, but a true liberty. Of all which points, I will ſpeake very briefly.</p>
            <p>As touching the firſt: for as much as Logicians <note place="margin">§. <hi>Sect. 3. The definition of Chriſtian libertie.</hi>
               </note> teach, <note n="a" place="margin">Ariſt. Poſter. 1. 14.</note> that the definition of the ſpeciall, is to be fetched from the diſtribution of the generall; for which cauſe, the <note n="b" place="margin">Plato in Sophista.</note> diuine Philoſopher calleth a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as being the ready, and as it were the Kings way to a definition: we will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take a ſuruey of the diuers ſorts of liberty. For there is an outward or externall liberty, and there is an inward or internall liberty. The former, is the liberty of the outward man from externall or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſeruitude; which may be called the corporall or ciuill liberty. Of this our Sauiour ſpeaketh not, though the Iewes would ſeeme ſo to vnderſtand him; but of the internall, which may well ſtand with the outward or ciuill bondage. For as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt noted them, <note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 8. 33, 34</note> thogh outwardly free, to be in ſpirituall bondage: ſo contrariwiſe, thoſe who in reſpect of the inner man are free, may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be ſubiect to the externall or ciuill ſeruitude; which nothing impeacheth or impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the liberty of the ſoule and conſcience before God. In which regard the Apoſtle ſaith; <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that is called in the Lord, being a ſeruant, is the Lords free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177216:7"/> So that the liberty whereof we ſpeake, is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the ſoule, or inner man. Wicked therefore is the doctrine of the Anabaptiſts, who thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt themſelues from all ſubiection to the ciuill Magiſtrate, vnder pretence of Chriſtian liberty. I call their doctrine wicked, becauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 16.</note> ſaith; that they who vnder pretence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty deny obedience to the Magiſtrate in lawfull things, doe vſe their liberty for a cloake to couer their wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, the inward liberty is either a carnall, or ſpirituall libertie. The carnal libertie is that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſoule of man is free from righteouſneſſe: which indeed is a voluntary ſeruice of ſinne. For when men bee free from righteouſneſſe, they are ſeruants of ſinne, and contrariwiſe; as the Apoſtle <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 20.</note> ſheweth. But our Sauiour ſpeaketh of a liberty, which, as it freeth men from the ſeruitude of ſin, and all the ſpirituall yokes of bondage, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the ſame; ſo it maketh them the ſeruants of righteouſneſſe. For when <hi>we are</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 18.</note> 
               <hi>made free from ſinne, we are made the ſeruants of righteouſnes.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as in reſpect of the former, we ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; He that is called, being a ſeruant, is the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Chriſt: ſo in reſpect of this latter, <note n="h" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 22.</note> he <hi>that is called being free, is the ſeruant of Christ.</hi> Diuelliſh therefore is the Doctrine of the Libertines, who vnder prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſtian liberty, diſcharge Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from all obedience to the law of God, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them free to do whatſoeuer themſelues thinke good. And ſuch is the ſlander of the Papiſts, laying that doctrine to our charge, who notwithſtanding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177216:8"/> are further from it then themſelues. For by the Popes indulgences and pardons, and the Prieſts abſolutions, ſetting men free from ſinne for ſmall, and oft times for ridiculous penances, what doe they elſe but teach men to make but a ſport of ſin? Of ſuch Libertines the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 19.</note> ſpeaketh, that whileſt they promiſe liberty to others, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are the ſeruants of corruption.</p>
            <p>It remaineth therefore, that Chriſtian liberty is a ſpirituall liberty, freeing the true Chriſtian from the ſeruitude of ſinne, and from all other yokes of ſpirituall bondage, wherewith ſinne had intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs.</p>
            <p>Neither is Chriſtian liberty onely priuatiue, as being a freedome and immunity from bondage; as though this were all, that by it we are not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: but as appeareth by this Scripture, it is alſo poſitiue, as being a liberty, power, right, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the priuileges of Gods children, who are alſo heires of God, and coheires with Chriſt. For when hee had ſaid that ſeruants abide not in the houſe for euer, but that ſuch as be ſonnes, abide in the houſe of God for euer; he inferreth, If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſonne ſhall make you free, you ſhall be free indeed. Giuing vs to vnderſtand, that thoſe whom he freeth, hee doth not onely make them not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, <hi>viz.</hi> of ſinne, but alſo ſonnes and heires of God, and citizens of heauen. Euen as they who are made freemen of London, or any other terreſtriall Citie, are not onely exempted from being ſeruants or apprentiſes; but alſo are indowed with the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and priuileges of free Burgeſſes and Citizens.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177216:8"/> So ſaith the Apoſtle, <note n="k" place="margin">Gal 4. 5. 6. 7.</note> Gal. 4. 5. that Chriſt hath redeemed thoſe who were vnder the law, that we might receiue the adoption of ſonnes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian liberty therefore is a ſpirituall liberty, which as the <note n="a" place="margin">Galath. 2. 4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The partition.</note> Apoſtle ſpeaketh, the faithfull haue in Chriſt Ieſus. That is the definition.</p>
            <p>The eſſentiall parts whereof generally it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, are two. For partly it is priuatiue, as being an immunity from all ſpirituall bondage; in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it is called in the Scriptures <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 9. 12. Luk 2. 38.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3. 24. Coloſ. 1. 14.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is redemption, and is ſometimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the verbes <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 2. 15.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <note n="e" place="margin">Col. 1. 13. 1. Theſſ. 1. 10.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliuerance: and partly it is poſitiue, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a right, title, and intereſt to the priuiledges and prerogatiues of Gods adopted children in Chriſt, the citizens of the Celeſtiall Ieruſalem: and in this reſpect it is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Ioh. 1. 12. to thoſe that receiue Chriſt by faith, he hath giuen <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, right or power to be the ſons of God, 1. Cor. 8. 9. Take heed, leſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, your <hi>libertie, right or</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>power, bee not an offence to the weake.</hi> Thus you ſee what this libertie is, and wherein generally it doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>The author of this libertie is Chriſt the Son of <note place="margin">The efficient or author of this libertie.</note> God, as it is heere ſaid: <hi>If the Son therefore ſhall make you free,</hi> &amp;c. ſo the Apoſtle calleth it <note n="g" place="margin">Galath. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the libertie which we haue in and by Christ:</hi> &amp; againe, <note n="h" place="margin">Galath. 5. 1.</note> the <hi>libertie wherewith Christ hath made vs free.</hi> For he is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 11. 26.</note> that <hi>Deliuerer which ſhould come out of Sion,</hi> who <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth vs</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Theſſ. 1. 10.</note> 
               <hi>from the wrath of God,</hi> from the tyrannie of Satan, <note n="l" place="margin">1. Iohn 3. 8.</note> diſſoluing the works of the diuell, <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 12. 29.</note> bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſtrong man and caſting him out, <note n="n" place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 15.</note> ſpoiling
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177216:9"/> principalities and powers, and <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 8.</note> leading captiuitie captiue; from the bondage of ſinne, for he is the <note n="p" place="margin">John 1. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world,</hi> whoſe blood doth <note n="q" place="margin">1 Iohn 1. 7. Heb. 9. 14.</note> cleanſe vs both from the guilt of ſinne, and alſo from the corruption: for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>he</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pet. 1. 18. Tit. 2, 14.</note> 
               <hi>gaue himſelfe for vs, that he might redeeme vs from all iniquitie, and might purge vs to bee a peculiar people to himſelfe, zealous of good workes.</hi> And hee is that perfect Sauiour, out of whoſe ſide iſſue both <note n="s" place="margin">Ioh. 19. 34. 35. 1. Ioh. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>blood and water;</hi> the blood of redemption, to free vs from the guilt of ſinne; and the water of abluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to cleanſe vs from the corruption. From the law <note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 4. 4.</note> for <hi>therefore was he borne of a woman, and made vnder the law, that he might redeeme them that were vnder the law.</hi> From death and damnation; for ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he became a <note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>curſe,</hi> that wee might bee freed from the curſe; therefore hee died, that <hi>through</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 2. 14. 15</note> 
               <hi>death he might vanquiſh him, who had the power of death, that is, the diuell; and that he might deliuer them, who through feare of death, were all their life time ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this needeth no proofe, for in that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him to be our redeemer, by whom wee haue <note n="x" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 7. 1. Cor. 1. 30.</note> redemption, we all acknowledge him to be the author of our libertie. Let vs rather conſider, how he procureth this libertie vnto vs. This he doth two waies; both meritoriouſly, and effectually. By his merit, in <note n="y" place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>giuing himſelf to be a price of ranſome for vs.</hi> For, as <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 18. 19</note> ſaith, we <hi>are redeemed not with any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible things, as ſiluer and gold, but with the precious blood of Christ,</hi> by <note n="a" place="margin">Heb 9. 12.</note> which <hi>blood he is entred once into the holy place, hauing procured an eternall redemption</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:177216:9"/> 
               <hi>for vs.</hi> Secondly, by the efficacie of his ſpirit, for we are not to imagine, that Chriſt hath only merited and purchaſed this libertie for vs; but that alſo he doth confer, applie, and beſtow it vpon vs: which he doth by giuing vnto vs his <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8. 9. 15. Gal. 4. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit.</hi> For, as in the naturall bodie, the animall ſpirit, which cauſeth ſenſe and motion, is from the head ſent into all the members of the bodie; ſo in the myſticall bodie of Chriſt, the <hi>Spirit of</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 51. 14.</note> 
               <hi>libertie</hi> is communicated to all his members; by which ſpirit he dwelleth in vs, and effectually worketh this libertie, in the degrees of our ſaluation, viz. vocation, iuſtification, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, glorification, (as you ſhall heare anon, and by the meanes of our ſaluation. The principall whereof is the preaching of the Goſpell, which is the <hi>Law</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iam. 1. 25.</note>, or doctrine of libertie, the miniſterie whereof was ordained to this end, to <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 26. 18.</note> 
               <hi>open</hi> mens <hi>eyes, to turne them from darkneſſe vnto light, and from the power of Satan vnto God, that by faith in Christ, they may receiue forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and inheritance with them that be ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This teacheth vs, that in our ſelues we are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, <note place="margin">The vſe of this doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</note> (for elſe we needed not a redeemer) and of our ſelues not able to free vs out of bondage, that there was no meanes to ſet vs at libertie, but the moſt precious ranſome, which Chriſt our bleſſed Sauiour paid for vs. That we ſhould acknowledge the infinite loue of God <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 3. 16. 1. Ioh. 4. 10.</note> the Father, who gaue his Sonne, and of the Sonne <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 15. 13.</note> who gaue himſelfe to be a ranſome for vs. That we may acknowledge our ſelues bound to be thankfull <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 107. 2. Col. 1. 12. 13. 14 Rom. 7. 25. 1. Cor. 15. 57.</note> vnto him, for <hi>let them giue thankes whom the Lord hath redeemed.</hi> That
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177216:10"/> we may highly eſteeme of this libertie, which coſt ſo deare a price: that with all diligence we vſe the meanes to obtaine it, and neuer be at reſt vntill we be made partakers of it: when we haue obtained it, to <note n="i" place="margin">Galath. 5. 1.</note> ſtand faſt in it; not to abuſe it to licentiouſnes, but to vſe it to the glorie of our Redeemer, who hath freed vs from the ſpirituall bondage of ſin and Satan, not that we might ſinne freely, but that we might <note n="k" place="margin">Luke 1. 74.</note> 
               <hi>ſerue God without feare, in holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes before him all the daies of our life.</hi> We muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that being <note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 19. 20</note> bought with a price, wee are not our own, but his that bought vs: and therefore ſhould not ſeek our ſelues, or ſerue our owne luſts, but ſhould glorifie him both in our ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which are not ours, but his that hath bought vs, &amp;c. And ſo much of the author of this libertie.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſubiect or parties to whom <note place="margin">§. 5. The ſubiect of this libertie, or parties on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is conferred.</note> this libertie belongeth, which by the context ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to be thoſe, who by the grace of adoption and regeneration, are made the ſonnes of God in Chriſt. For naturally we are all ſeruants, ſeruing a moſt ſeruile and ſlauiſh ſeruitude vnder ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; which muſt ſeriouſly be acknowledged of vs, before we will either truly deſire to be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this libertie, (for none need to be freed, but thoſe that are in bondage) or will profit by this doctrine, as appertaining vnto vs. Our Sauiour therefore, according to the <note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 61. 1.</note> propheſie of <hi>Eſay,</hi> ſaith, <note n="n" place="margin">Luke 4. 18.</note> that he was ſent to <hi>preach libertie and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the captiues,</hi> and <hi>to ſet at libertie the broken hearted.</hi> He came to ſeek and to <hi>ſaue</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 18. 11.</note> 
               <hi>that which was lost:</hi> neither came he to <note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 9. 13.</note> 
               <hi>call the righteous</hi> (in their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177216:10"/> owne conceits) <hi>but ſinners vnto repentance:</hi> to fill the <note n="q" place="margin">Matth. 5. 3. 6.</note> poore and the hungry <note n="r" place="margin">Luke 1. 53.</note> with good things, whileſt the rich are ſent emptie away.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we deceiue our ſelues with this conceit, that becauſe we profeſſe our ſelues to be redeemed, and do liue in the houſe of God which is his viſible Church, therefore we haue all attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this libertie alreadie. For in the houſe of God, there be as well <note n="s" place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 20.</note> veſſels of diſhonor, as veſſels of honor; in the <note n="t" place="margin">Matth. 3. 12.</note> floore of God, as well chaffe as wheate; in the <note n="u" place="margin">Matth. 13. 47</note> net of God, as well bad fiſh as that which is good; in the <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 13. 24</note> field of God, as well tares as corne; in the familie or houſe of God, as well <note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 8. 34. 35.</note> ſeruants as ſonnes; in the flocke of God, as well <note n="y" place="margin">Matth. 25. 32. 33.</note> goates as ſheep. Vnleſſe therfore you be the ſons of God by faith, truly called, engrafted into Chriſt as his members, regenerated by the Spirit of God, this libertie as yet doth not belong vnto you. For it is a libertie, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <note n="z" place="margin">Galath. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>which we haue in Christ,</hi> that is, which we being in Chriſt haue by him, as after we ſhall heare: (which alſo) is confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon vs, in and by our vocation, iuſtification and ſanctification; and therefore none enioy it, as actually made free, but ſuch as are ſanctified, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and called.</p>
            <p>But heere ſome will obiect: Are not wee the Church of God, and is not the Church a company of men called? haue we not been baptiſed, and by baptiſme regenerated, made the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt, and children of God? How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do you ſay, we are not free? Beloued, as this obiection is not vnlike the cauill of the captious Iewes in this place; ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177216:11"/> muſt it receiue the like anſwere. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay vnto you,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>he that committeth ſin is the ſeruant of ſinne, and the ſeruant ſhall not abide in the houſe,</hi> &amp;c. I know that you are the Church of God, as theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> were; and that you haue been bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as they had been circumciſed. But you muſt diſtinguiſh, firſt, of the Church; that there is a Church viſible, and a Church inuiſible, which is the myſtical body of Chriſt. And you are to know, that there bee many in the Church viſible, which are not <note n="a" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 19.</note> of the Church inuiſible; many in the houſe of God, which be ſeruants and not ſonnes. Secondly, of calling; that there is an outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by the Word, which is common to all in the Church, of which it is ſaid, <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 20. 16 and 22. 14.</note> many called, and few choſen. And there is an inward and effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, according to Gods <hi>purpoſe,</hi> of which it is ſaid, <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8. 28. 30</note> whom he elected, he called. Thirdly, of Baptiſme; there is an outward Baptiſme, which is the ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <note n="d" place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 21.</note> fleſh with water, and an inward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, wherein the ſouſe is <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 12. 24. 1. Pet. 1. 2.</note> ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, and with the water of the holy Ghoſt, whereof the outward is a ſigne. Fourthly, of vnion with Chriſt, for there is a ſacramentall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Baptiſme, &amp; a ſpirituall by the <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 13.</note> holy Ghoſt &amp; by faith. Laſtly, of Chriſtians, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt, ſonnes of God. For as the Apoſtle diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 2. 28. 29</note> Iewes, that they were either outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Iewes and in ſhew, or inwardly and in truth; and our Sauionr in the next <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 8. 37. &amp;c.</note> words, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the promiſe. For as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>they</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:177216:11"/>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 3. 7.</note> 
               <hi>which bee of faith, are the ſonnes of Abraham:</hi> ſo men are called Chriſtians, members of Chriſt, ſonnes of God, not onely who are ſuch indeede and in truth; but alſo ſuch as are Chriſtians onely in profeſſion, members of Chriſt in appearance, <note n="k" place="margin">Ezech. 16. 20. 21. Matth. 8. 12.</note> ſonnes of God in reſpect of the outward coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Wherefore though you liue in the viſible Church, though you be called, though you haue been baptized, and by baptiſme ſacramentally vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the body of Chriſt, which is his Church; though in your owne profeſſion, and in the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of others, who conceiue of you (as they ought) according to the iudgement of charitie, you are Chriſtians, members of Chriſt, and ſonnes of the kingdome: notwithſtanding, if you doe not truely beleeue in Chriſt and vnfainedly repent of your ſinnes, you are ſeruants and not ſonnes. Yea, ſo farre ſhall theſe outward priuiledges be from exempting you from damnation, that they ſhall greatly aggrauate your iudgement. For hath God called, vs and we are not called? hath he inuited vs to turne vnto him, and we are not conuerted? hath he by his Miniſters <note n="l" place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 20.</note> intreated vs, that we would be reconciled vnto him, and we will not be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? hath he offered vs infinite mercy in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of our ſaluation by Chriſt, and we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the ſame, not caring to apprehend the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God and merits of Chriſt, but ſuffering his precious blood to be ſpilt as it were on the ground in vaine? hath he often ſought <note n="m" place="margin">Matth. 23. 37</note> to gather vs vnto him, as the Hen gathereth the Chickens vnder her wings, and we would not? Then haue the meanes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177216:12"/> of ſaluation been the meanes of obduration vnto vs; and the Word, which to the faithfull is the <note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 2. 16.</note> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of life vnto life, vnto vs is become a ſauour of death vnto death. Yea, for this contempt of the Goſpell, if we perſiſt in it, our eſtate in the day of iudgement ſhall be more <note n="o" place="margin">Matth. 10. 15.</note> intolerable, then theirs of Sodom and Gomorah. And vnto vs belongeth that fearful wo denounced by our Sauiour Chriſt, <note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 11. 21. 23.</note> Woe to thee Chorazin, woe to thee Bethſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, woe to thee Capernaum: for if the meanes which you haue had, had been vouchſafed to them of Tyrus and Sidon, yea to them of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they would haue turned vnto God, but <hi>I ſay vnto you, it ſhal be eaſier for them in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then for you.</hi> Againe, hath the Lord ſent his Sonne to redeeme vs, giuen vs meanes to applie Chriſt vnto vs, hath he entreated vs to beleeue and repent, and put to his ſeale in Baptiſme, thereby aſſuring vs, that if we beleeue and repent, our ſoules are waſhed with the blood of Chriſt, that we are ingrafted into him, and in him are made the ſons of God, and heires of eternall life? Shall not wee therefore moſt worthily periſh in our ſinnes, if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we will not beleeue and repent; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially hauing in our Baptiſme by a ſolemne vow bound our ſelues therto. The conſideration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt force men, who are not yet regenerated, vnfainedly to turne vnto God, &amp; to lay hold vpon Chriſt by faith. For it is moſt certaine, though they liue in the houſe of God, which is his Church, yet vntill they truly beleeue and repent, they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and not ſonnes: and ſuch ſeruants as are held
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177216:12"/> vnder the moſt miſerable and baſeſt ſlauerie of fin and Satan: being not only bound hand and foot, yea in heart and mind, ſo that they can neither doe nor thinke that which is ſpiritually good; but are alſo caried away <note n="q" place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 26. Titus 3. 3.</note> captiue, to performe the will of Satan, and the luſts of the fleſh; whereby it comes to paſſe, that as they can do no good, ſo can they do nothing but ſinne.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be conſidered, is the qualitie of this liberty, viz. that it is a ture liberty. For neither <note place="margin">§. 6. The qualitie or propertie of this libertie.</note> is it an imaginarie libertie, as in the paradox of the Stoicks, who held that wiſe men of the world were only free, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they alſo, being not freed by Chriſt, were and are no better but ſeruants; or in the ſecure imaginations of carnal men, who with theſe Iewes, though being in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, think the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues free. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it a looſe liberty or licentiouſnes, ſuch as Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines aſſume to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, but a true &amp; a holy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, wherby we being freed from ſin, become ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of righteouſnes, &amp; being deliuered from the hands of our ſpiritual enemies, are inabled to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God with willing minds, &amp; chearefull hearts: for that is the only true libertie: &amp; ſuch is the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Saints in heauen, and of the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who count it not only their libertie, but alſo their happines, willingly and cheerefully to ſerue the Lord. For if the Sonne, who is the truth, ſhall make you free, then ſhall you be free <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, indeed, and in truth.</p>
            <p>This therefore, as it ſerueth for the comfort of the godly; ſo alſo for the terror of the wicked. For, from this ſpeech of our Sauiour, we may conclude
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177216:13"/> both waies. 1. Whoſoeuer are made free by Chriſt, they are free indeed: but all the faithfull are made free by Chriſt; therefore (whatſoeuer the diuell or their owne corruption can obiect to the contrarie) they are free indeed.</p>
            <p>Againe, If the Son make you free, ſaith Chriſt, then are you free indeed; but you (ſay I to vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers and impenitent ſinners,) are not free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: <hi>For he that committeth ſin, is the ſeruant of ſin;</hi> therefore, howſoeuer you profeſſe your ſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by Chriſt, and howſoeuer alſo it be moſt true, that Chriſt hath paid a ranſome ſufficient for the redemption of all; yet are you not actually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, nor the benefit of redemption applied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, vntill you bee ingrafted into Chriſt by faith, and renued by the holy Ghoſt. And the ſame may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the oath of the Lord, <hi>(wherein</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Hebr. 6. 18.</note> 
               <hi>it is impoſsible that he ſhould lie,)</hi> the oath which he ſware to our father <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that he would giue vs, both that we ſhould be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand, that is, the power and dominion of our ſpirituall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and <note n="s" place="margin">Luk. 1. 73. 74.</note> being <hi>deliuered, ſhould alſo haue grace to worſhip God without feare, in holines &amp; righteouſnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, all the daies of our life.</hi> If therfore we do not endeuour to worſhippe God in holines and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, with willing minds and vpright hearts; it is as ſure as the oath of the Lord is true, that as yet we are not actually freed and redeemed by Chriſt. For <hi>if the Sonne make you free, you ſhall be free indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much of the general doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie: wherein I haue been the ſhorter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all theſe points, wherof I haue thus generally
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177216:13"/> and briefely ſpoken, viz. that Chriſtian libertie is a ſpirituall libertie, which the faithfull haue in and by Chriſt Ieſus; that it conſiſteth on two parts, an immunitie and freedome from all ſpirituall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and right to the priuiledges and liberties of Gods children: that Chriſt our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is the author of this libertie, both in reſpect of his merit and efficacie: that it is beſtowed only vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faithfull, who are the ſonnes of God and members of Chriſt: and laſtly, that this libertie of Chriſtians is a true libertie; all theſe points, I ſay, will more plainly and fully appeare in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, whereunto we are now to deſcend.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie therefore, is either <hi>libertas</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Viae,</hi> of this life, ſuch as is incident <note place="margin">§. 7. The ſpeciall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie.</note> vnto vs whiles we are in the way, whereof <note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 12. 58.</note> ſome not vnfitly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our Sauiour to ſpeake. Luk. 12. 58. <hi>Giue diligence to be deliuered from thy aduerſarie, whiles thou art in the way,</hi> &amp;c. vnderſtanding by the Gouernor, God; by the Iudge, Chriſt; by the aduerſarie, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, ſin, a guiltie conſcience, the ſentence of the law; by the way, this life; by the officer the Angels, by priſon, hell, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Patriae,</hi> of the life to come, which we ſhall enioy, when being come to the end of our way, wee ſhall haue the <note n="u" place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 9.</note> end of our faith; which is the ſaluation of our ſoules.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The former is freedome from the bondage of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177216:14"/> ſinne, the other from the <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note> bondage of corruption. The former is ſimplie called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="x" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 7. 14.</note> redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the latter <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the redemption of poſſeſſion: for by the former we are heires, <hi>ſpe,</hi> in hope and expectation; by the latter, <hi>re,</hi> in deed and poſſeſſion; the one is begun and in part, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfect and complete: the one, the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of grace, the other, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the libertie of glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in order: And firſt of the libertie of <note place="margin">The libertie of grace.</note> grace, which euen in this life the faithfull do enioy in and by Chriſt. And it is either common to all the faithfull, as well of the old Teſtament as of the new; or peculiar to the faithfull vnder the Goſpel. The faithfull vnder both Teſtaments were and are ſonnes; who as they haue the ſame <note n="z" place="margin">Titus 1. 4.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon faith; ſo haue they the ſame <note n="a" place="margin">Jud. 3.</note> common ſaluation, and therfore the ſame libertie and right, in reſpect of the inheritance it ſelfe, and all the degrees thereof. Notwithſtanding, there is difference betweene ſonnes vnder age, and in their minoritie, in reſpect of diſcipline and gouernment, and thoſe who are come to yeares: the former being nurtured by ſchoolemaſters, and gouerned by tutors, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4. 2. 3. &amp; 3. 24.</note> of the faithfull before the incarnation of Chriſt; the latter ſet at libertie from ſuch diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and gouernment. Otherwiſe, as they had the ſame faith, and the ſame iuſtification (for all the faithfull both before Chriſt and after, were and are iuſtified by faith, as <hi>Abraham</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 4. 23. 24</note> was, Rom. 4. and by ſuch <note n="d" place="margin">Iam. 2. 20. 21.</note> a faith, Iam. 2.) ſo haue they the ſame libertie which is obtained by faith, and in ſome chiefe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177216:14"/> points thereof is, as <note n="e" place="margin">Jnstit. lib. 3. cap. 19. §. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, an appendix of iuſtification.</p>
            <p>The common libertie of grace, which may fitly <note place="margin">The libertie of ſauing grace.</note> be called the libertie of ſauing grace, containeth many particulars; which, for your eaſieſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, may be reduced to theſe three heads.</p>
            <p>For it is a libertie which wee haue in and by our
<list>
                  <item>Vocation.</item>
                  <item>Iuſtification.</item>
                  <item>Sanctification.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For, although theſe three concurre in time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man is no ſooner effectually called, but he is alſo iuſtified before God, and no ſooner iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, but hee beginneth alſo to bee ſanctified (which is duely to be obſerued of thoſe, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming, and that perhaps for a long time, that they be called and iuſtified, doe ſtill remaine vnſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) notwithſtanding in order of nature <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8. 30.</note> vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on goeth before iuſtification, and iuſtification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſanctification. And let this alſo by the way be obſerued for the comfort of the godly. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, profeſſing the true faith, hath a true pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and vnfained deſire to walke before God in the obedience of his will, making conſcience of all his waies: that man, howſoeuer beſides his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall purpoſe he may faile (<note n="g" place="margin">Jam. 3. 2.</note> as we all doe) in many particulars; yet he is ſanctified, and from his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification may certainely conclude, that he is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, that he is called, that he is elected, that he ſhall be ſaued. For the fruite could not bee good, vnleſſe the tree or the branch that beareth it were good, and the branch cannot be good, vnleſſe it be ingrafted into Chriſt, <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 15. 1. 5.</note> the onely true vine: that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177216:15"/> is to ſay, a mans conuerſation is neuer acceptable vnto God, before his perſon be accepted; and his perſon is not accepted, vntill hee bee vnited vnto Chriſt. For the better vnderſtanding of this point, wee muſt remember, that Chriſt at a deare price hath long ſince purchaſed this liberty for vs, and hath meritoriouſly wrought our freedome. But none are actually and effectually ſet at libertie, but thoſe alone, who haue actuall vnion and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt. Now in our effectuall vocation, we haue vnion with Chriſt; and in our iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſanctification, communion with him. In the former, in reſpect of his merits apprehended by faith, and communicated vnto vs by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in the other, in reſpect of his graces, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him without meaſure, are by his ſpirit from <note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 1. 16.</note> him deriued, and in ſome meaſure communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs by infuſion.</p>
            <p>But let vs ſpeake of them ſeuerally. And firſt, as <note place="margin">§. 8. The libertie of Vocation.</note> touching our vocation, I ſay with the Apoſtle, <note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 5. 13.</note> Gal. 5. <hi>Brethren, you are called vnto libertie:</hi> which words we are thus to vnderſtand, that by our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling we are not only inuited vnto Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in generall, as a maine benefit of our Chriſtian profeſſion; but alſo by it are enfranchiſed, being thereby put into poſſeſſion of a good part of it, and entituled to the reſt. For whereas naturally we are wholy, and not onely in part (for that may be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the faithfull, Rom. 7. 14.) carnall, ſold vnder ſinne; by our calling we are firſt made ſpirituall, being in ſome meaſure indued with the ſpirit of Chriſt. Now the ſpirit of Chriſt, being the <hi>ſpirit of</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177216:15"/> 
               <hi>libertie,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh, <note n="i" place="margin">Pſalm. 51. 14.</note> Pſalm. 51. we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue with the Apoſtle, <note n="m" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 17.</note> that <hi>where the ſpirit of the Lord is, there is liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the liberty which we haue by our calling ſtandeth on theſe degrees. Firſt, as it is an immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; our mindes are therein freed from the ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of blindneſſe and incredulitie, our hearts and willes from the bondage of that, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 11. 32.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (vnder which all men natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are concluded) that is, diſobedience and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; our ſelues, from the ſeruitude of Satan, being called and as it were culled out of the world, whereby is meant the company of worldly men, which is the kingdome of the diuell, (who is the <note n="o" place="margin">Iohn 12. 31.</note> Prince, yea the God <note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor 4. 4.</note> of the world, working ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="q" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 2.</note> in the children of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie and diſobedience, blinding their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and <note n="r" place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 26.</note> captiuating their willes:) and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſlated from the moſt ſlauiſh eſtate of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, being <note n="s" place="margin">Apoc. 14. 4.</note> redeemed from among men, and deliuered out of the <note n="t" place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.</note> world, which becauſe it wholy, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">1. John 5. 19. For he is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of whom he had ſpoken, verſe 18.</note> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lieth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſubiection of the diuell, (who hath the <note n="*" place="margin">Hebr. 2. 15.</note> power of death) is alſo ſubiect to death and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>As it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a power and intereſt; wee are in our calling indued, as I ſaid, with the ſpirit of libertie, which freeth our ſoules by enlightening our minds, perſwading our iudgements, and ſofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our hearts, enſpiring thereinto godly deſires and gracious reſolutions; whereby he beginning the grace of faith in vs, doth regenerate vs and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177216:16"/> vnite vs vnto Chriſt. So that by our effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in regard that therein the ſpirit of libertie is communicated vnto vs, and the ſauing grace of faith is therein begotten in vs, wee are made the ſonnes of God and members of Chriſt, and are not only entituled to all the rights and priuiledges of the children of God, and members of Chriſt; but alſo are preſently <note n="x" place="margin">Iohn 5. 24.</note> tranſlated, as it were from death to life, and from the ſtate of damnation, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate of grace and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>But theſe things doe neede ſome further expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Firſt, therefore in the miniſterie of the Goſpell, which is the miniſterie <note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 8. 1. Pet. 1. 23.</note> of the ſpirit, the <note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 10. 8.</note> word of faith, the ſeede of regeneration, the <note n="a" place="margin">Jam. 1. 18. 25.</note> lawe or doctrine of liberty, and the ordinarie meanes of our <note n="b" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 14.</note> vocation, the Lord, preuenting vs with his grace, ſendeth the ſpirit of his ſonne into our hearts; which being, as I ſaid, the ſpirit of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie; firſt, freeth our minds from the bondage of ignorance, incredulitie and vanitie, wherein vntill then we were held captiue, not once able of our ſelues to entertaine a <note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 5.</note> good thought, the whole frame of our thoughts being <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 6. 5. &amp; 8. 21.</note> onely euill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually; the wiſdome of our fleſh, <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> or that which our fleſh mindeth, being emnitie againſt God; our ſelues, not onely not perceiuing, but being <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 14.</note> not able to perceiue the things which are of the ſpirit of God, and much leſſe able to giue aſſent vnto them (for no man can ſay that <note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 3.</note> Ieſus is Chriſt but by the holy Ghoſt) and much leſſe to aſſent effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, or by a liuely faith. The ſpirit of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the miniſterie of the word (which is a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177216:16"/>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 105</note> light vnto our feete) as the meanes, and by the Miniſters of the Goſpell as his inſtruments (who are therefore called the <note n="i" place="margin">Matth. 5. 14.</note> light of the world, and are ſent by Chriſt to <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 26. 18.</note> open our eyes, and to giue light to them that ſit in <note n="l" place="margin">Luk. 1. 79.</note> darkeneſſe, and in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of death) enlighteneth our minds to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and openeth our hearts as he did the heart of <hi>Lydia,</hi> perſwading our ſoules <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 16. 14.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, not onely to attend, but, as the word alſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, to aſſent to thoſe things which are ſpoken by the Miniſters; and thereby maketh vs vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly to acknowledge and ſeriouſly to conſider, both our miſerable ſeruitude and damnable eſtate in our ſelues, and alſo the gracious libertie and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing grace of God offered in Chriſt. And this is the firſt degree of the libertie which wee haue in our calling, that therein we are called out of <note n="n" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 9.</note> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into light. Of this liberty the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, 2. Cor. 3. <note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 15. 16. 17.</note> that whereas there is naturally a vaile ouer mens hearts, that they cannot vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Word; this vaile is taken away by the ſpirit of God, when they turne vnto the Lord. Now the <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the ſpirit, and where the ſpirit of the Lord is, there is libertie.</hi> In this regard the ſpirit is compared to an <note n="p" place="margin">Apoc. 3. 18.</note> eye-ſalue, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that <note n="q" place="margin">1. Joh. 2. 27.</note> anointing, which, being receiued from Chriſt, teacheth vs all things.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus reuealed vnto vs both our owne miſerable eſtate in our ſelues, and the infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in Chriſt, and moued vs truely to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto; in the next place hee toucheth our hearts with a ſenſe of our miſery, and with a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177216:17"/> of ſinne, which hath brought vs into that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate, and by the miniſterie of the Word, which is his <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> power to our ſaluation, &amp; his <note n="s" place="margin">Eſai. 53. 1.</note> arme to draw vs vnto him, he turneth our will and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from darkneſſe (which naturally <note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 3. 19 Act. 16. 18.</note> we loue) vnto light, not only working in vs hartie deſires, to come out of that damnable eſtate, and to be made partakers of Chriſt (which deſires alſo he being the <note n="u" place="margin">Zac. 12. 10. Rom. 8. 26.</note> Spirit of ſupplication, helpeth vs to expreſſe in hartie prayer;) but alſo inſpiring into vs a ſetled re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that for as much as libertie and ſaluation is promiſed to all that receiue Chriſt by faith; we will therfore reſolue vndoubtedly to acknowledge him to be our only Sauiour, and to reſt vpon him alone for ſaluation. Thus by working, 1. In our minds an effectuall aſſent to the promiſe of the Goſpell. 2. In our hearts an earneſt deſire to bee made partakers of Chriſts merits, and 3. In our will a ſetled reſolution, to acknowledge him to be the Meſſias, and to relie vpon the mercies of God and merits of Chriſt, for iuſtification and ſaluation, (by which three we do <note n="*" place="margin">John 1. 12.</note> receiue Chriſt), the Spirit of God begetteth the grace of iuſtifying faith in vs. In the begetting whereof, he doth not only <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 26. 18.</note> turne men from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan vnto God; but alſo regenerateth them, and vniteth them vnto Chriſt, making them of the children of wrath, the ſonnes of God; of the impes of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> members of Chriſt; and of the ſubiects of Satan in the kingdome of <note n="y" place="margin">Coloſ. 1. 13.</note> darknes, fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <note n="z" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 19.</note> citizens with the Saints in the kingdome of God. And this is the liberty which we haue by our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177216:17"/> calling. As for the teachers of free will, and the magnifiers of our pure naturals; they neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the woful bondage wherein we are by nature, nor the happie libertie, whereunto we are, not borne, but called. For this is a libertie, <hi>ad quam non nati, ſed renati ſumus;</hi> which we haue not by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, but by regeneration. Neither is it a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon libertie of al, but a libertie peculiar to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, who are a people <note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 9.</note> ſet at libertie, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the ſonnes of God, and members of Chriſt. But it will be ſaid, if there be no freedome in our willes before we be called, then belike we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſaued againſt our willes, and we muſt look with the Enthuſiaſts for violent raptures. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that there is in our willes a freedome of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby it is free from compulſion. For, that the will ſhould be forced, it implieth a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for then it ſhould both will and nill the ſame thing at one time. Notwithſtanding this freedome of the will, vntill it be freed by grace, is a voluntary ſeruice of ſinne; voluntarily and with greedineſſe, willing that which is euill, although it can will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe. But the preuenting grace of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are called, is perſwaſiue, and that ordinarily by the Word; drawing vs indeed, and ſo of vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling making vs willing, but this is by perſwaſion, and not by compulſion. For although our willes in the firſt act of our conuerſion be meerely paſſiue, and none can come to Chriſt vnleſſe the <note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 6. 44.</note> Father draw him: yet we can no ſooner conceiue a man to be effectually called, then that he is made wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For in the very act of our calling, of vnwilling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177216:18"/> we are made willing; and no ſooner are we effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally drawne, but we willingly come: in whch ſenſe true is that ſaying of <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God indeed draweth, but he draweth him that is willing. Wherefore though our willes doe not concurre, <hi>ad vocationem,</hi> vnto our calling; yet they concurre, <hi>in vocatione,</hi> in our calling, being therein made free.</p>
            <p>Now we are to intreate of the libertie which we <note place="margin">§. 9. Justification and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to be confounded.</note> haue both in our iuſtification, and alſo in our fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification. For howſoeuer theſe graces do alwaies ſo concurre, as that whoſoeuer hath the one, hath the other; and whoſoeuer hath not both, hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet are we carefully to diſtinguiſh them. For the Papiſts in not diſtinguiſhing them, confound the Law and the Goſpell, aboliſh the maine bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Chriſt, which in the Scriptures goeth vnder the name of iuſtification, and with it the libertie which we haue by it; and laſtly, by their Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine teach men to place the matter of their iuſtification, and the merit of ſaluation in themſelues. For they do teach, that a man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, when he is made righteous by righteouſneſſe inherent in himſelfe, and performed by himſelfe, and accordingly make two degrees of iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The one, which they call the firſt iuſtification, when a man of a ſinner is made iuſt, by the infuſion of faith, hope, and charitie; the other, which they call the ſecond iuſtification, when a man of a iuſt man is made more iuſt by bringing forth good workes. So that according to their doctrine, the righteouſnes of the firſt iuſtification, is habituall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177216:18"/> and inherent in themſelues; of the ſecond, actuall, and performed by themſelues. And whereas iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication ſtandeth on two parts, viz. remiſſion of ſin, and the making, or, as the <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5. 19.</note> Apoſtle ſpeaketh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting of vs righteous; as they teach, that we are made righteous; not by imputation, but by infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of righteouſnes: ſo they teach, that remiſſion of ſinne is the deletion of ſinne, and that ſinnes are then pardoned, when by infuſion of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie graces they are expelled. Euen as water is then ſaid to be warmed, when by the acceſſion of heate the cold is expelled. Againe, where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, that we are iuſtified by grace, that is, by <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 24.</note> the meere fauour of God in Chriſt, by faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes, by the righteouſnes of God, which without the law is manifeſted in the Goſpell; they by grace vnderſtand the graces of God in vs, which they ſay concurre with faith vnto iuſtification; by righteouſneſſe, not the righteouſnes of Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by faith, but a righteouſnes from Chriſt infuſed into vs, &amp;c. Which doctrines, being vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſanctification, are for the moſt part true. For we do not deny, but that the matter of our ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is inherent in vs, and performed by vs; and that it is partly habituall, and partly actuall; that it conſiſteth in our dying vnto ſinne, which is called mortification, and liuing vnto righteouſnes, which is called viuification: that there be degrees thereof, according to the meaſure of grace recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: that we are ſanctified by the grace, or rather graces of God in vs; and that thereunto not faith alone, but hope and charitie, &amp; other both inward
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177216:19"/> graces and outward obedience do concurre, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But if the iuſtification which the Papiſts teach, be nothing elſe but ſanctification; what then is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of that, which in the Scriptures goeth vnder the name of iuſtification, and is the maine benefit of the Meſſias, wherby we are not only freed from the guilt of ſinne, which bound vs ouer to death and damnation; but alſo are in Chriſt accepted as righteous, and made heires of eternall life; by which we are freed from the feare of damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and are entitled vnto the kingdome of heauen? Surely by the Popiſh doctrine it is in a manner aboliſhed, and with it the libertie which we haue by it, which is no leſſe then our deliuerance from hell, and our title to the kingdome of heauen, which if we haue not by Chriſt, we haue no ſaluation by him. For it is certaine, that whereby we are iuſtified, thereby we are ſaued.</p>
            <p>This moſt pernicious and Antichriſtian error they ſeeke to iuſtifie by the like notation of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine words. For, as to be ſanctified, is to be made holy, by holines wrought in vs; ſo to be iuſtified, in their conceit, is to be made iuſt, by righteouſnes wrought in vs.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwere, that if the Latine notati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were to be reſpected, it would not hinder our cauſe. For, we do freely confeſſe, that whom the Lord iuſtifieth, he maketh iuſt. But then the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, whether by imputation, or by infuſion. By imputation, we ſay, as he iuſtifieth; by infuſion, not as he iuſtifieth, but as he ſanctifieth. But the Latine word is no further to bee vrged, then as it is the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177216:19"/> tranſlation of the Hebrew word in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of the Greeke in the new, which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to iuſtifie. Now it is plaine, that both the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the greeke <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is <hi>verbum forenſe,</hi> a iudiciall word aſcribed vnto God, as the Iudge; to teach vs, when we thinke of iuſtification, to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon our ſelues before the iudgement ſeat of God. And in this ſenſe it is oppoſed to condemning, as in the <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 25. 1. Prou. 17. 15.</note> iudgements of men, Deut. 25. 1. Prou. 17. 15. ſo in the <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 12. 37. 1. King. 8. 32. Rom. 5. 16. 18. Rom. 8. 33.</note> iudgement of God, Matth. 12. 37. By thy words thou ſhalt be iuſtified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned; 1. King. 8. 32. Rom. 5. 16. 18. and Rom. 8. 33. Hereby then appeareth, both what iuſtification is, and wherein it differeth from ſanctification. For the contrarie to ſanctifying, is polluting; but the contrarie to iuſtifying, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning. Wherfore, as ſanctifying being the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to polluting, doth ſignifie making holy; ſo iuſtifying being the contrarie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demning, doth ſignifie abſoluing, acquitting, pronouncing iuſt. And in this ſenſe euermore, in the queſtion of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, it is vſed when it is aſcribed vnto God. Neither are the Papiſts able to produce any one teſtimonie, where iuſtification being aſcribed to God, (as <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 3. 26. &amp; 8. 33.</note> It is God that doth iuſtifie) doth ſignifie making righteous by infuſion. This then is the firſt note of difference, whereunto others may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For in iuſtification, as I ſaid before, we haue communion with Chriſt, in reſpect of his merits imputed vnto vs, to free vs from the guilt of ſinne, and feare of damnation, and to entitle vs to the kingdome of heauen. In ſanctification we haue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177216:20"/> communion with Chriſt in reſpect of his graces, which being in him without meaſure, are by his ſpirit deriued to vs in meaſure, and communicated by infuſion, to free vs from the corruption and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of ſinne, and to prepare and fit vs for the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The matter therefore of Iuſtification, or that whereby we are abſolued, and in reſpect whereof, God doth acquit vs from our ſinnes, and accepting vs as iuſt, doth ſo pronounce of vs, is the merits, righteouſneſſe, and obedience of Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. For by what we are redeemed, by that we haue <note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 7. Coloſ. 1. 14.</note> remiſſion of ſinnes, or iuſtification; but we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed only by the merits and righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and not by our owne; and therefore we are iuſtified by the righteouſnes of Chriſt, and not by that which is inherent in vs, or performed by vs: but our ſanctification conſiſteth in the graces of Gods ſpirit inherent in vs, and the new obedience performed by vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> We are iuſtified by imputation of Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, when God imputing to a belieuer the righteouſnes of Chriſt, and accepting of it in the belieuers behalfe, as if he had performed it in his owne perſon, doth not only acquit him from his ſinnes, but alſo accepteth of him as righteous in Chriſt, and as an heire of eternall life. For as Chriſt was made a ſinner for vs, ſo are we made <note n="h" place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 21.</note> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before God in him: Chriſt was made a ſinner for vs, by imputation of our ſinnes to him: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are made righteous before God in him, by imputation of his righteouſnes vnto vs. Againe, as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177216:20"/> we were made ſinners, that is, guiltie of the firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams tranſgreſſion; <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 5. 18. 19</note> ſo are we iuſtified by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> But we are guiltie of the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion by imputation. For how ſhould that being an action, and therefore tranſient, be communicated vnto vs? Let <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> anſwere: It is communicated to vs, ſaith he, <note n="k" place="margin">Adae peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no bis commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatur per ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationem eo modo, quo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municari poteſt id quod tranſit, nimirum per imputationem. Omnibus enim imputatur, qui ex Adamo naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am omnes in lumbis Adami existentes, in eo et per eum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauimus, cum ipſe peccauit. Bellarm. tit. 3. de amiſſ. grat. &amp; ſtat. pec. lib. 5. cap. 17.</note> as tranſient things vſe to be communicated, that is to ſay, <hi>by imputation.</hi> Therefore we are iuſtified by imputation of the obedience of the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> For the obedience of Chriſt which he performed on earth, being tranſient, how could it be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated vnto vs, but as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, all tranſient things are communicated, viz. by imputation? The reaſon of which imputation is this. For as all men being in <hi>Adam</hi> as the roote of mankind, originally, are guiltie of his ſin, it being imputed vnto them, becauſe in him &amp; by him, by reaſon of their vnion with him, all ſinned: ſo the faithfull being in Chriſt as their head or root, are iuſtified by his obedience, it being imputed to them, becauſe in him, and by him, by reaſon of our vnion with him, we fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Law, and in him, and by him we ſatisfied the iuſtice of God. But we are ſanctified by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of grace wrought in vs by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Iuſtification is the verie intitling of vs to the kingdome of heauen. Sanctification is both the badge and cognizance, whereby they are to bee diſcerned and knowne who are iuſtified, and ſhall be <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 26. 18. &amp; 20. 32.</note> ſaued, and the fitting and preparing of vs to that kingdome, whereinto no vncleane thing ſhall enter.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:177216:21"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The righteouſnes of iuſtification is perfect, (for it is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt) and therefore of iuſtification it ſelfe there are no degrees, though of the aſſurance thereof there be degrees, according to the meaſure of faith. The righteouſneſſe of our ſanctification, which is inherent, is vnperfect in this life, and ſtayned with the fleſh; and thereof there are degrees, as we grow in grace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> We are both iuſtified and ſanctified by faith, but in diuers reſpects. We are iuſtified by faith, becauſe by it we apprehend the righteouſnes of Chriſt, and therefore are iuſtified by it, not formally, as it is a power or habit in vs, or as it is a part of inherent righteouſnes, but relatiuely in reſpect of the obiect which it doth apprehend; and by it alone we are iuſtified, becauſe it is the onely grace in vs, which apprehendeth the merits of Chriſt to iuſtification. Wee are ſanctified by faith, as a chiefe part of our ſanctification, being as it were the roote, both of other inward graces, and outward obedience: but we are not ſanctified by it alone, becauſe not only other graces inherent, but alſo outward obedience concurre thereto.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus premiſed, let vs conſider what <note place="margin">§. 10. The libertie of iustification.</note> that libertie is, which we haue both in our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and alſo in our ſanctification. In both (as our freedome is an immunitie) we are freed from ſinne, and from the Law, which is the ſtrength of ſinne, though in different reſpects, which will be ſo many more differences betwixt iuſtification and ſanctification. In ſin there are two things, the guilt therof, and the corruption. In iuſtification we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177216:21"/> are freed wholly from the guilt of ſinne: for to be iuſtified, is to haue remiſſion of ſin <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 4. 6. 7. Freedome from guilt of ſinne.</note>, Rom. 4. 6. 7. or, which is all one, to be freed, or abſolued from the guilt of it. And ſo certaine it is, that in iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we haue this freedome, that to be iuſtified, is to be freed, according to the Scriptures phraſe <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 6. 7.</note>, Rom. 6. 7. <hi>He that is dead, is freed from ſin:</hi> the Greek is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. See <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 13. 38. 39.</note> Act. 13. 38. 39. <hi>Be it knowen vnto you, that through Christ is preached vnto you forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. And from all things, from which you could not be iustified by the law of Moſes, by him euery one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth is iustified.</hi> Where, to be iuſtified, is to haue pardon of ſinne, or freedome from the guilt of it.</p>
            <p>The guilt of ſin is the obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or binding ouer of the ſinner vnto puniſhment: and this bond is partly in the Law, <note n="*" place="margin">As the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</note> which is the hand-writing or obligation that is againſt vs, binding ouer the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of it, to the puniſhment threatned in it; and partly in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or aſſumption.</note> conſcience, applying the Law, morall or naturall, to the ſinner, and from thence <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or concluſion.</note> pronouncing him ſubiect to puniſhment. From this obligation or guilt we are freed before God, and as it were in the court of heauen, ſo ſoone as we beleeue: and we are freed from the ſame in the court of conſcience, when we know that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and are aſſured of our iuſtification. For, <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 26. 18.</note> by faith we haue remiſſion of ſinne: and whoſoeuer <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 13. 38 39</note> beleeueth in Chriſt, he is iuſtified from the guilt thereof.</p>
            <p>This our freedome containeth in it happineſſe, for as their eſtate is miſerable, whoſe ſinnes are not forgiuen, becauſe by their ſins they are debtors vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177216:22"/> God, owing in reſpect thereof eternal death and damnation (though they only feele this burthen, whoſe conſcience is throughly touched, of whom it is ſaid, <note n="r" place="margin">Prou. 18. 14.</note> A wounded ſpirit who is able to beare?) ſo their eſtate is happie, who are freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the guilt of ſinne. <hi>Dauid,</hi> though a King, flouriſhing in great honor, wealth, and delights; notwithſtanding he repoſeth his felicitie in the forgiuenes of ſin, <note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 32. 1. 2. Rom. 3. 6.</note> Pſal. 32. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe wickedneſſe is forgiuen, and whoſe ſinne is couered, bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord imputeth not iniquitie.</hi> Which ſhould moue vs aboue all things to labour for the forgiueneſſe of ſin, and for the aſſurance thereof. If thou beleeue in Chriſt, and withall confeſſe thy ſin <note n="t" place="margin">1. Joh. 1. 9.</note> and forſake <note n="u" place="margin">Prou. 28. 13.</note> it, thou mayeſt be ſure that it is pardoned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in our iuſtification we are freed from the <note place="margin">§. 11.</note> the <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 4. 4. 5. Freedome from the Law.</note> law, and that in two reſpects. Firſt, from the malediction or condemnation of it: ſecondly, from the lawes exaction of inherent and that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſnes vnto iuſtification. Vnder which double yoke of bondage all men are, that are not iuſtified by faith in Chriſt: that is, all men in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are ſubiect to the curſe <note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 3. 10.</note> who in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree doe at any time in their whole life tranſgreſſe any part of the law, as all men oftentimes doe; and again, no man who is not in Chriſt, can be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the curſe, and attaine to iuſtification, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he continue in all the things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of the law to doe them; which no man is able to doe, the lawe by reaſon of the fleſh being <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 8. 3.</note> impoſſible vnto vs. Let naturall or vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted men apply this to themſelues. Canſt thou
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177216:22"/> not by the ſentence of the law be exempted from the curſe, vnleſſe thou doſt not onely not commit the things forbidden, but alſo doe the duties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded; vnleſſe thou doſt all, and vnleſſe thou continueſt in doing all, neuer failing in any one particular; and finally, vnleſſe thou continueſt in doing all, and euery thing commaunded in that perfect manner and meaſure which the lawe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth? Alas then, how wilt thou eſcape the dreadfull curſe, who in ſtead of doing the duties commaunded, haſt done the vices forbidden; who in ſtead of keeping all the commaundements, haſt broken them all; and in ſtead of continuing in a totall perpetuall and perfect obedience of the lawe, haſt continued in the diſobedience thereof? Hence we may conclude with the Apoſtle, that all men in themſelues, euen thoſe <note n="z" place="margin">Gal. 3. 10.</note> who ſeeke to be iuſtified by the lawe, bee concluded vnder ſinne, and conſequently vnder the curſe: and therefore haue extreame neede to ſeeke vnto Chriſt, that by him they may be ſet free from this twofold bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; which is, to be vnder the curſe of the lawe if we breake it, when we can doe nothing elſe but breake it; and to be excluded from iuſtification, if we doe not continue in the perfect performance of the lawe, when we are not able ſo much as to <note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 5. Freedome from the curſe of the Law.</note> thinke a good thought, or once to will that which is ſpiritually good. But by Chriſt we are freed from both. Firſt from the curſe, as the Apoſtle in expreſſe tearmes teacheth: <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the lawe, when he was made a curſe for vs.</hi> He hath freed vs from the puniſhment of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177216:23"/> ſinne, by vndergoing the puniſhment for vs, hee hath acquitted vs from our debts by diſcharging them for vs. For as <hi>Eſay</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eſa. 53. 3.</note> ſaith, <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſsions, he was broken for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace</hi> (that is, which was to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vs peace and reconciliation with God) <hi>was laide vpon him,</hi> and <hi>by his ſtripes we are healed.</hi> And againe, <note n="d" place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath laide vpon him the iniquitie of vs all,</hi> that is, the puniſhment of all our ſinnes. And, <note n="e" place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> 
               <hi>My righteous ſeruant by his knowledge,</hi> that is, by the knowledge of him or faith in him, <hi>ſhall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie many, for he ſhall beare their iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, by the curſe of the law from which Chriſt doth free vs, we are to vnderſtand all euill <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 91. 10.</note> of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as well temporall as eternall: for it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to imagine with the Papiſts, that Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing freed vs from the eternall puniſhment, hath not freed vs from the temporall. By temporall, we meane the euils both of this life, whether corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſpirituall (which are innumerable) and alſo in the ende of this life, <hi>viz.</hi> an euill death. Againſt both theſe it will be obiected, and firſt againſt the former; that notwithſtanding their iuſtification, the faithfull are as ſubiect to afflictions and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of this life as others, and therefore to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But I deny that conſequence, if you ſpeake of puniſhments properly, which be the curſes of the law inflicted vpon men by way of vengeance, to ſatisfie the iuſtice of God. For the Lord hath impoſed the puniſhment of all our ſinnes vpon Chriſt; who hath fully ſatisfied the iuſtice of his Father for them. And therefore as there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177216:23"/> ſo no puniſhment (properly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus. Neither can it ſtand with the iuſtice of God (who is not onely mercifull, but alſo <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 3. 25. 26. 1. John 1. 9.</note> iuſt in iuſtifying of vs) to exact a puniſhment of the faithfull for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of his iuſtice, for whom Chriſt hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fully ſatisfied his iuſtice by bearing the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: this were to puniſh the ſame ſinnes twice, once in Chriſt, and againe in vs. Indeed the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are ſubiect to croſſes and afflictions: but all the afflictions of the godly are either trials for their good, or ſuch iudgements as are either ſimply fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly chaſtiſements proceeding from loue, and meerely reſpecting the good of the party chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 1. Cor. 11. 32. <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 32.</note> 
               <hi>When we are iudged we are chaſtiſed of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemned with the world,</hi> or elſe they be alſo <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (according to the <note n="i" place="margin">Of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> honor, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> care.</note> etymologie of the word which by ſome is giuen) when God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the chaſtiſement of the party, hath alſo care or reſpect to his owne honour, which would be impeached, if hee ſhould ſeeme to winke at the ſcandalous offences of his children, as though he would maintaine them in their ſins. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard iudgement, as <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 17.</note> ſaith, beginneth at the houſe of God. For the Lord many times correcteth thoſe ſins in the godly, both for his owne honor, and their good, which he ſeemeth to paſſe by in the wicked. Of this kind we haue an example in <hi>Dauid,</hi> to whom the Lord vpon his ſubmiſſion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaue his grieuous ſins of murther and adulterie, notwithſtanding both for <hi>Dauids</hi> chaſtiſement,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177216:24"/> and for the example of others, but chiefely for the maintenance of his owne glorie (which by the ſcandalous offences of Gods children, is by the wicked blaſphemed, as though ſuch ſins were the fruits of the religion and ſeruice of God), he would not ſuffer the child begotten in adulterie to liue. Why? becauſe by that ſin <hi>Dauid</hi> had <note n="l" place="margin">2. Sam. 12. 14.</note> cauſed the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme. The vſe which we are to make hereof, is, not with the Papiſts, to teach men to make ſatisfaction to God for their ſins, as though Chriſt had not fully ſatisfied for them alreadie: but to teach men, both to beware that they do not commit ſin, eſpecially ſcandalous ſins; becauſe thereby they diſpleaſe and diſhonor God their mercifull Father, prouoking him to powre his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vpon them, for their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned with the world, and for the maintenance of his owne honor: and alſo that hauing ſinned, we do <note n="m" place="margin">Amos 4. 12.</note> meete the Lord in his iudgements, by humbling our ſelues before him, confeſſing our fault, and crauing pardon, that <note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 31.</note> iudgeing our ſelues, we may not be iudged of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Againſt the ſecond it is alſo obiected, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their iuſtification, the godly die as well as the wicked. I anſwere, that as of all afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo alſo of death, the nature is changed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the faithful; to whom death it ſelfe, though brought in by the malice of the diuel, is not a curſe or puniſhment properly. I do not denie, but that many times, in reſpect of the time and manner of death, the godly are iudged and chaſtiſed, the Lord
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177216:24"/> in mercie killing their bodies, that he may <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 30. 32.</note> ſaue their ſoules; but from the euill of death they are wholly freed: for to them it is the end of ſinne, and is therefore inflicted vpon vs, that ſinne might die with vs, as <hi>Methodius</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Apud Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. haereſ. 64.</note> ſaith, and being the end of ſin vnto vs, it is alſo the end of miſerie, the hauen of reſt, a happie paſſage out of this vale of miſerie vnto the kingdome of glorie; and ſo not onely no curſe, but alſo a bleſſing, no loſſe, but an aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as after we ſhall ſhew. For yet we ſpeake but of the immunities of iuſtification, the principall whereof yet remaineth to be ſpoken of; that is, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from ſubiection to damnation, to euerlaſting death, to the eternall wrath of God, which is the moſt miſerable bondage and ſubiection of al thoſe, who are not iuſtified by faith in Chriſt. But fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this curſe alſo Chriſt hath freed the faithfull. For this is the immunitie which we haue by him; that <note n="q" place="margin">John 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhall not periſh,</hi> that there is <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8. 1.</note> 
               <hi>no condemnation to them that be in Christ Ieſus;</hi> that by his death <note n="s" place="margin">Hebr. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>he hath destroyed him that had the power of death, that he might deliuer them all, which for feare of death, were all their life time ſubiect to bondage;</hi> that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Sauiour deliuereth vs from the <note n="t" place="margin">1. Theſ. 1. 10.</note> wrath to come.</p>
            <p>And thus wee haue heard of two immunities, which wee haue in our iuſtification: that wee are freed from the guilt of ſinne, and from the curſe of the Law, whereto our ſin had made vs ſubiect. And from hence ariſeth vnſpeakeable peace and libertie to the diſtreſſed conſcience, terrified with the guilt of ſinne, the curſe of the Law, and feare of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177216:25"/> when it receiuing Chriſt by faith, hath immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and freedome from them all.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the other immunitie from the <note place="margin">§. 12. Freedome from the lawes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> law, in reſpect of the exaction of perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be inherent in vs, and perfect obedience to be performed by vs, vnto our iuſtification and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: vnto which yoke of bondage, as I ſaid, all men by nature are ſubiect. For it is ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that without righteouſnes, and ſuch a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as is fully anſwerable to the perfect law of God, no man can be iuſtified.</p>
            <p>Now, this righteouſnes muſt either be inherent in our ſelues, which is the righteouſneſſe that the Law requireth vnto iuſtification; or being perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by another, (which is Chriſt) for vs, muſt be imputed vnto vs: and that is the righteouſneſſe which the Goſpel propoundeth vnto iuſtification.</p>
            <p>A third righteouſnes, whereby wee ſhould bee iuſtified, cannot be named. If therefore we be not partakers of Chriſts righteouſnes apprehended by faith, we muſt ſtand to the ſentence of the Law; which is, either to performe perfect and perpetuall obedience, or not to bee iuſtified. But if Chriſts righteouſnes be imputed vnto vs (as it is to all that apprehend it by faith) then are <hi>we iustified,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſentence of the Law, <hi>by</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 3. 28. Galath. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>faith,</hi> (that is, by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt apprehended by faith) <hi>without the workes of the Law,</hi> that is, without any reſpect of obedience performed by our ſelues. And in this libertie from the Law, ſtandeth the chiefe comfort and ſtay of a Chriſtian, when hee ſummoning himſelfe, as it were in the court of his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177216:25"/> conſcience before the iudgement ſeate of God, to be iuſtified, or condemned, ſhall conſider that by Chriſt he is freed, both from the condemnation of the Law, and from the exaction of inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes to iuſtification: ſo that he ſhall not need to ſtand to the ſentence of the Law, or to truſt to any obedience performed by himſelfe, as it were to a broken ſtaffe, wherein there can be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, (for if God ſhould enter into <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 143. 2.</note> iudgement with vs according thereto, no man liuing could be iuſtified) but may ſafely &amp; freely, without reſpect, either of his owne obedience, or of the ſentence of the law, relie vpon the mercies of God, and merits of Chriſt; that for as much as the Lord hath giuen him grace to beleeue, &amp; by that faith hath <note n="x" place="margin">Hoſ. 2. 10.</note> eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to Chriſt, and vnited him vnto him as his member; he hath alſo communion in Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, whereby without regard to any righteouſneſſe of his owne, he is iuſtified before God.</p>
            <p>Againſt this part of Chriſtian libertie, which is moſt comfortable, the Church of Rome (as it well becomes the ſynagogue of Antichriſt) doth by might and maine oppoſe it ſelfe: contending, not only that we are iuſtified by righteouſneſſe inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; but alſo that the ſame obedience, which the Law preſcribeth, is in greater perfection required in the Goſpel vnto iuſtification. By which doctrine of theirs, they confound the Law and the Goſpell, and in ſo doing aboliſh the couenant of grace, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate the maine promiſe of the Goſpell, which is the charter of our libertie, the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of our faith, the foundation of all our aſſurance for iuſtification
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177216:26"/> and ſaluation. For if the Goſpell promiſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound iuſtification and ſaluation, vpon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our owne obedience, and that in more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection then the law it ſelfe required: then is it not only a couenant of workes, as well as the law, but alſo impoſeth a heauieryoke vpon mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then the Law did. But it is manifeſt that the Goſpell is the couenant of grace made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Galath. 3. 8. 16. 17.</note>, concerning iuſtification by faith in Chriſt; whereas the Law contrariwiſe is the couenant of workes, which 430. yeares after was deliuered by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and did not diſanull the former promiſe, concerning iuſtification by faith. The condition wheron the Goſpell promiſeth iuſtification, is faith in Chriſt; the condition of the Law, our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect &amp; perpetual obedience. For the Goſpel <note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 10. 5. &amp;c.</note> ſaith; If thou beleeue in Chriſt, thou art iuſtified &amp; ſhalt be ſaued: the Law, If thou doſt theſe things, thou ſhalt liue thereby. The righteouſnes exacted in the law to iuſtification, is a righteouſnes both habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all inherent in our ſelues, and actuall performed by our ſelues. The righteouſnes <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 3. 21. 22</note> which without the Law is reuealed in the Goſpell, is <hi>the righteouſnes of God,</hi> that is, of Chriſt who is God, (for he is <note n="b" place="margin">Jerem. 23. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> our righteouſneſſe, and was giuen vnto vs of God <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 30.</note> to be our righteouſneſſe) <hi>by the faith of Ieſus Christ, vnto all, and vpon all that beleeue,</hi> that is, the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, who is God (though not the righteouſnes of the Deitie, as <hi>Oſiander</hi> thought, but the righteouſneſſe both inherent in him, as he was man, as his innocencie and holineſſe, and alſo performed by him, as his paſſiue and actiue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177216:26"/> being apprehended by faith, is according to the doctrine of the Goſpell, imputed to euery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer vnto iuſtification.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt is our righteouſneſſe, and <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 10. 4.</note> 
               <hi>end of the Law vnto righteouſneſſe to all that beleeue,</hi> that <hi>whoſoeuer</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">John 3. 16. Mark. 16. 16.</note> 
               <hi>beleeueth in Christ ſhall be ſaued,</hi> it is the maine doctrine of the Goſpell, the chiefe article of our religion, the charter of our inheritance, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance which we haue of ſaluation: which we are ſo to hold, as that if an <note n="f" place="margin">Galath. 1. 8. 9.</note> Angell from heauen ſhould teach vs another Goſpell, or propound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs another way of iuſtification, (as namely, by inherent righteouſnes, and our owne obedience) we ought to hold him accurſed, and our ſelues alſo, if we yeeld to him. For whoſoeuer looke to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the obedience which the Law preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, they <note n="g" place="margin">Galath. 5. 4.</note> are ſeparated from Chriſt, and fallen from grace.</p>
            <p>We doe not deny, but that the Goſpell teacheth repentance as well as faith; and commendeth the duties of ſanctification, as well as it promiſeth iuſtification. Yea, as it promiſeth the grace of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification to thoſe that beleeue; ſo to them that are iuſtified and redeemed, it promiſeth the <note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 1. 74. Jer. 31. 33. 34.</note> grace of ſanctification by the ſpirit, whereby they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled in ſome meaſure to worſhip God in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe. We doe alſo confeſſe, that a greater meaſure of knowledge and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is required of the faithfull vnder the Goſpell, then was vnder the Lawe; becauſe to whom more is giuen, of them more is required, and the greater benefit requireth the greater duties of thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177216:27"/> But when the queſtion is of the matter of our iuſtification, and merit of our ſaluation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we being ſinners and loſt in our ſelues, ſhould bee iuſtified before God, and entituled vnto the kingdome of heauen; what that is, whereby we are abſolued from our ſinnes, and accepted as righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and as heires of eternall life; what that is, which will ſtand in iudgement before God, and which we may truſt vnto, when we appeare before the iudgement ſeat of God, why the ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſhould not be pronounced againſt vs; what that is, whereby wee are redeemed from death, and reconciled vnto God, or, as the ſcripture vttereth the ſame thing in other tearmes, <note n="i" place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 19. Epheſ. 1. 7.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we haue remiſſion of ſinnes: it is moſt plaine, that the doctrine of the Goſpell placeth the whole matter of iuſtification, and merit of ſaluation in the righteouſneſſe and obedience of Chriſt alone; by whoſe blood, as the Apoſtle <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 5. 9. 18. 19.</note> ſpeaketh, and by whoſe obedience, we are iuſtified. As for that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is in herent in our ſelues, though infuſed of God, and that obedience which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by our ſelues, though proceeding from grace; the Goſpell teacheth vs, in the queſtion of iuſtification, <note n="l" place="margin">Philip. 3. 8. 9.</note> to eſteeme it as droſſe and dung, yea as loſſe, that we may gaine Chriſt, and may be found in him, not hauing our own righteouſneſſe, which is preſcribed in the lawe, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God through faith.</p>
            <p>This therefore is the liberty which we haue by the grace of iuſtification, that wee are freed from
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177216:27"/> that miſerable bondage of the law, which exacteth an obedience and righteouſneſſe inherent vnto iuſtification, which no man is able to performe, and therefore holdeth men in ſubiection to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, engendring with <hi>Agar,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Galath. 4. 24. &amp;c.</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, none but ſeruants, which ſhall not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with the children of the free woman, that is, who are begotten by the Goſpell, to be the heires of that righteouſneſſe which is by faith.</p>
            <p>And thus much of the libertie of iuſtification as <note place="margin">§. 13. The libertie of iustification as it is a right, with the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof.</note> it is an immunitie. For as it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or right, it alſo containeth many notable priuiledges.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that we are not onely freed from the guilt of ſinne, but alſo are accepted and pronounced iuſt, and by imputation of Chriſts, both <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 5. 9. 19.</note> paſſiue and actiue obedience made righteous, which <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 4. 6. 7. 2. Cor. 5. 21.</note> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately followes vpon the former, ſo that by our iuſtification we are not onely made not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but alſo ſtand righteous before God, and that, by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that we are not onely freed from the curſe of the lawe, but alſo are made partakers of the <note n="p" place="margin">Galath. 3. 13. 14. 16.</note> bleſſedneſſe promiſed to <hi>Abraham, viz.</hi> that in his <note n="q" place="margin">Geneſ. 22. 18.</note> ſeede, which is Chriſt, the faithfull of all nations ſhould bee bleſſed. But this will beſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the particulars: for the faithfull are not onely freed from the euils of this life, whether cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall or ſpirituall, as they be curſes; but they are all turned into bleſſings vnto them. For this is the priuiledge of the faithfull, that the Lord cauſeth all things, whether good or bad, <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8. 28.</note> 
               <hi>To worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the good of thoſe that doe loue him.</hi> In which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177216:28"/> ſenſe <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <note n="s" place="margin">Pſalm. 1. 3.</note> that <hi>all things ſucceede well with the righteous man.</hi> As for afflictions, he both profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in particular of himſelfe, <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 71.</note> that <hi>it was good for him that he had been afflicted;</hi> and alſo in generall, pronounceth the man <note n="u" place="margin">pſal. 94. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed, whom the Lord doth chaſtiſe and teach in his lawe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, corporall death is not onely no loſſe to the faithfull, but alſo an aduantage; becauſe in it they change a ſinfull and mortall life, for a life bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and immortall. It is not onely no curſe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a bleſſing: for it is not onely the end of ſinne and miſerie, but the beginning of perfect and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting happineſſe: whereupon the holy Ghoſt <note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 14. 13.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth them all <hi>bleſſed that die in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither are the faithfull onely freed from feare of damnation, but alſo are put in aſſurance of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, being <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8. 24.</note> ſaued in hope, which is the chiefe happineſſe that can be enioyed in this life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we are not onely freed from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the lawe, exacting of vs perfect obedience vnto iuſtification, but wee haue alſo liberty to pleade the righteouſneſſe propounded in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace; and to appeale from the ſentence of the lawe, to the promiſe of the Goſpell; from the tribunall of iuſtice, to the throne of grace; and in the queſtion of iuſtification not at all to regarde our owne obedience, but wholly to reſt vpon the mercies of God and merits of Chriſt our ſauiour.</p>
            <p>Vpon this liberty of iuſtification follow other priuiledges. For firſt, whereas by nature we are the children of wrath; now, <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 5. 1.</note> 
               <hi>being iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:177216:28"/> who hath <note n="z" place="margin">Coloſ. 1. 20. 21</note> reconciled vs to his Father.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whereas ſin maketh a <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 59. 2.</note> ſeparation betweene God and vs, ſo that naturally we ſhunne the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, as of a ſeuere Iudge; being iuſtified by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, wee alſo haue free <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5. 2. Epheſ. 3. 12. 1. John 5. 14.</note> acceſſe vnto God by faith, and haue libertie with boldneſſe and aſſurance that we ſhall be heard, to make our requeſts to God in the name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Vpon our iuſtification by faith, we are endued with the <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5. 5. Epheſ. 1. 13. Rom. 8. 15. 16. Galath. 4. 6. Epheſ. 4. 30.</note> ſpirit of adoption, which aſſureth vs of Gods fatherly loue towards vs, teaching vs to crie in our hearts, <hi>Abba Father;</hi> by which, being the earneſt of our inheritance, wee are ſealed vp vnto the day of our full redemption.</p>
            <p n="4">4 With the hope of ſaluation, which is <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8. 23. Tit. 2. 13.</note> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of iuſtifying faith, and a conſequent of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, whereby we liue in expectation of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 With ioy <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5. 2. 3. 1. Pet. 1. 8.</note> in the holy Ghoſt, which <hi>Peter</hi> calleth ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious. For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle denying that the libertie of Chriſtians doth chiefely ſtand in <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 14. 17.</note> meat and drinke, and in the free vſe of outward things; ſheweth alſo wherin it prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally doth conſiſt. For <hi>the kingdome of God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not meate and drinke, but righteouſnes,</hi> which is the priuiledge of iuſtification it ſelfe, <hi>and peace and ioy in the holy Ghost,</hi> which are conſequents of the former.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, with perſeuerance. For <note n="g" place="margin">John 8. 35.</note> the Son abideth in the houſe for euer, being <note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſafely kept by the power of God through faith vnto ſaluation. For if
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177216:29"/>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8. 17.</note> ſons, then heires, heires of God, and coheires with Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the libertie which we haue in <note place="margin">§. 14. The libertie of ſanctification. 1. From the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of ſin.</note> our ſanctification, and ſo farre forth as we are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified. Now our ſanctification in this life being but in part, ſo is this libertie: which, as it is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie, is alſo a freedome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage of ſin, and of the Law; though in other reſpects, then thoſe that haue been mentioned in the libertie of iuſtification.</p>
            <p>For, in iuſtification we are freed from the guilt of ſin; in ſanctification, from the corruption of ſin. But heere we are to conſider, how farre forth wee are ſet free therefrom. For the hypocriticall Papiſts teach, that when a man is regenerated, or as they alſo ſpeake, iuſtified, originall ſin is ſo aboliſhed, as that it doth not only not raigne, but not ſo much as remaine or liue in the partie ſanctified. By which doctrine they teach men to bee deſperate hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, either fearing their conſcience, that they may haue no ſenſe of ſinne, and may pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with this conceit, that they haue no ſinne; in which reſpect the ſaying of <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 19.</note> is verified of them, That whiles they promiſe libertie to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and others, they are indeed ſeruants of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: or if they haue any ſenſe of ſin dwelling in them, they muſt perſwade themſelues they are not ſanctified, nor iuſtified, and therefore not to be ſaued: ſuch miſerable comforters they are of poore ſinners, as to perſwade them that they haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, vtill ſin be quite aboliſhed in them.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177216:29"/> But this doctrine they teach contrarie to the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent teſtimonies of Scripture, contrarie to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall experience of the faithfull, contrarie to the light of their owne conſcience; that they might thereby vphold their Antichriſtian doctrine of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by inherent righteouſneſſe, and of the merit of good workes, which otherwiſe would fall to the ground. For, if in reſpect of originall ſin, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining and dwelling in vs, wee bee in our ſelues ſinners; how can we be iuſtified by inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes? If our beſt actions be ſtained with the fleſh, and our righteouſneſſes <note n="l" place="margin">Eſay 64. 6.</note> bee like polluted clouts; how ſhould they merit eternall life?</p>
            <p>We are therefore to hold, that in regeneration we are freed from the corruption of ſin; not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and at once, but in part, and by degrees; that ſin (though mortified in part, and we freed from the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of it, that it raigne no more with ful ſwinge and authoritie in vs) ſtill remaineth and dwelleth in vs, hindering vs from good, prouoking vs vnto euill, defiling and contaminating our beſt actions, neuer ſuffering vs with the full conſent of <note n="m" place="margin">Galath. 5. 17.</note> will, to performe or deſire that which is good. As the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle plainely ſheweth by his owne example, Rom. 7. <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 7. 14. &amp;c.</note> where the concupiſcence remaining in him, is not only plainly called a ſin, but deſcribed as a ſin, &amp; as an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or a repugnancie to the law of God: the ſenſe whereof (though the Papiſts haue no ſenſe of it) made the holy Apoſtle crie out, <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 7. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this bodie of death?</hi> Accurſed therfore was the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent <note n="p" place="margin">Seſſ. 5.</note>, which confeſſing that the Apoſtle
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177216:30"/> calleth it a ſin; notwithſtanding pronounceth them accurſed, that ſhall ſay it is a ſinne. But if we ſay we haue no ſin, we deceiue our ſelues, ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. John 1. 8.</note>, and there is no truth in vs.</p>
            <p>The freedome therefore which we haue in our ſanctification, which as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, is but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in this life, is not from the being of ſin in vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together and at once, though we be freed from it, in part and by degrees, but from the dominion of it, that we ſhould no more be feruants of ſin, but being freed from ſinne, might become feruants of righteouſnes, Rom. 6. 6. 18. which <hi>Augustine</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Jn Ioh. tract. 41.</note> did well obſerue out of the words of the Apoſtle, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting vs that ſin ſhould not remaine in our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodies. <hi>He doth not ſay, let it not be; but, let it not raigne: for whiles thou liueſt, it cannot be auoided, but that ſin wilbe in thy members; neuertheleſſe let dominion be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from it,</hi> &amp;c. Of this libertie the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Rom. 8. <note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 8. 1.</note> the <hi>law of the ſpirit of life which is in Chriſt, hath made me free from the law of ſinne and of death.</hi> That is, the power of the quickning Spirit, which being in Chriſt our head, and from him communicated vnto vs, doth rule in vs as a law, doth free vs from the power of ſin which worketh death, that it no more haue dominion (as it were a law) in vs. And Rom. 6. <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 6. 2. &amp;c. ad 12.</note> hauing proued, that ſin neither doth, nor can any more raigne in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: becauſe after the ſimilitude of Chriſts death and reſurrection, they are dead to ſin and riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and therefore, as death can no more haue dominion ouer Chriſt, being riſen from death, no more can ſin haue dominion ouer the faithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177216:30"/> once riſen from the graue of ſinne: afterwards, verſ. 14. he aſſureth the faithfull, that ſin ſhall <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 6. 14.</note> not haue dominion ouer them, becauſe they be not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, but vnder grace. Likewiſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. John 3. 9. John 8. 34.</note> ſaith, <hi>He that is borne of God, doth not commit ſin,</hi> namely, as a ſeruant of ſin: yea, he addeth, that <hi>he cannot ſin,</hi> namely, with full ſwinge and conſent of will, as thoſe which be ſeruants of ſin; becauſe the ſeed of God remaineth in him, whereby he is partly ſpirit, and not only fleſh. And therefore as he cannot perfectly wil that which is good, becauſe of the reluctation of the fleſh; ſo can he not will with full conſent, that which is euill, becauſe of the reluctation of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee are in our ſanctification freed <note place="margin">§. 15. 2. Freedome from the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the law.</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Law. But we are here alſo to conſider, <hi>quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> how farre forth. For the <note n="x" place="margin">Bellarm. de iustif. lib. 4. cap. 5. &amp;c. 1.</note> Papiſts charge vs, that we place Chriſtian libertie in this, that we are ſubiect to no law in our conſcience, and before God; and that we are free from all neceſſitie of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good works: which is a moſt diuelliſh ſlander. For although they abſurdly confound iuſtification and ſanctification; yet they know we do not: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they ignorant, but that we put a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene them in this reſpect. For though we teach that the obedience of the Law is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in vs to iuſtification, but that wee are freed from the exaction of the Law in that behalfe: yet we deny not, but that vnto ſanctification the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Law is required, and wee by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of dutie, bound to the obſeruation thereof. We confeſſe that to be free from obedience, is to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:177216:31"/> be the ſeruants of ſin, and the willing and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full worſhip of God, in <note n="y" place="margin">Luk 1. 74.</note> holines and righteouſnes without feare, to bee true libertie. Wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the morall law of God is perpetuall and immutable; and that this is an euerlaſting truth, that the creature is bound to worſhip and obey his Creator, and ſo much the more bound, as he hath receiued greater benefits. Indeed we ſay with <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">De libert. Christ.</note> that in our iuſtification we are reſtored to a ſtate of iuſtice, from which <hi>Adam</hi> fell; but yet, as we teach that we are no more bound to obedience, that thereby we might be iuſtified, then <hi>Adam</hi> who was alreadie iuſt; ſo we profeſſe, that in allegiance and thankfulnes, we are more bound to obey then he, yea, we profeſſe that God doth therefore free vs from the curſe, and the bondage of the law, that wee might bee inabled with freedome of ſpirit to obey it; and that being freed from ſin <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6. 18.</note>, we are made the ſeruants of righteouſnes. We teach, that God hauing ſworne <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 1. 73. 74.</note>, that to thoſe whom he iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, he will giue grace to worſhip him in holines and righteouſnes; no man can be aſſured of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification without obedience: that ſanctification being the end of our <note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 4. 1. Theſſ. 4. 7. Titus 2. 14. Epheſ. 2. 10.</note> election, calling, redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and regeneration, it is a neceſſarie conſequent of ſauing grace. We teach and profeſſe, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer good works do not concurre with faith, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the act of iuſtification, as a cauſe thereof; yet they concurre in the partie iuſtified, as neceſſarie fruits of faith, and teſtimonies of iuſtification. And as we teach with <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 3. 28. Galath. 2. 16.</note> that faith alone doth iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; ſo with <hi>Iames</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Jam. 2. 14. &amp;c.</note>, that the faith which is alone
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177216:31"/> doth not iuſtifie. Wee teach, that the blood of Chriſt, as it acquitteth vs from the guilt of ſin; ſo doth it alſo purge <note n="f" place="margin">Hebr. 9. 14.</note> our conſciences from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God; that <hi>he bare</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 24.</note> 
               <hi>in his bodie vpon the croſſe our ſinnes, that we being deliuered from ſinne, ſhould liue in righteouſneſſe:</hi> that whom Chriſt doth iuſtifie by faith, them he doth ſanctifie by his Spirit; that <hi>whoſoeuer</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 17.</note> 
               <hi>is in Chriſt, he is a new creature,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 5. 24.</note> crucifying the fleſh with the luſts therof, and <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8. 1.</note> walking not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit. We profeſſe that good workes are neceſſarie to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, though not <hi>neceſsitate efficientiae,</hi> as cauſing it, as the Papiſts teach; yet <hi>neceſsitate praeſentiae,</hi> as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſarie fruits of our faith, whereby we are to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, and to teſtifie our thankfulneſſe, to doe good to our brethren, and to make ſure <note n="l" place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 10.</note> our electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, calling and iuſtification vnto our ſelues; as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie foreru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners of ſaluation, being the vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted badges of them that ſhall bee ſaued, being the way wherein we are to <note n="m" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 10.</note> walke to euerlaſting life, being the euidence according to which God will iudge vs at the laſt day. And laſtly, that as by iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication God doth entitle vs vnto his kingdome; ſo by ſanctification he doth fit and prepare vs therto.</p>
            <p>We do not therefore by the doctrine of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation through faith, aboliſh the Law, but rather as the Apoſtle ſaith <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 3. 31.</note>, ſtabliſh it. For the more a man is aſſured of his free iuſtification, the better he is enabled, and the more he is bound to obey it.</p>
            <p>But although we be bound to obey the Law, as the ſubiects of God, and ſeruants of righteouſnes; and although the Law hath ſingular vſe in thoſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177216:32"/> that are iuſtified, (as being a rule of direction for our obedience, in the performance of the duties of pietie towards God, of iuſtice towards our neighbour, of ſobriety towards our ſelues; and a glaſſe of detection, to manifeſt the imperfections of our obedience, to keepe vs from Phariſaiſme: and laſtly, a rodde of correction, in reſpect of the fleſh or the olde man, yet remaining in vs, that by precepts, by exhortations and comminations, it more and more may bee mortified in vs, and wee kept from the ſpirit of ſlumber and ſecurity:) yet notwithſtanding wee are <hi>not vnder the lawe,</hi> as the Apoſtle <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 6. 14.</note> ſaith, <hi>but vnder grace.</hi> Wee are therefore in our ſanctification freed, though not from the obedience, yet from the ſeruitude and bondage of the law, and that in three reſpects:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of the irritation of it. In which <note place="margin">§ 16. Freedome from the irritation of the Law.</note> regard eſpecially the lawe is called the <note n="p" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 56.</note> ſtrength of ſinne: not that the lawe cauſeth or prouoketh ſinne properly, for the <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 7. 12.</note> law is holy, iuſt and good; but onely by accident, and occaſionally. For ſuch is the corruption of our vntamed <note n="r" place="margin">Nitimur in vetitum ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, cupimuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> negata. Gens humana ruit in vetitum nefas.</note> nature, vntill we be renewed by the ſpirit of God; that when the law, which is holy and good, forbiddeth ſinne, ſeeking to ſtoppe the courſe of our concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to bridle our ſinfull affections; thereby our vntamed corruption rebelleth ſo much the <note place="margin">Quod non licet, acrius vrit.</note> more; &amp; that it might appeare <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 7. 13. 8.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>exceedingly ſinfull,</hi> by occaſion of the lawe worketh in vs all manner of concupiſcence. Euen, as a deepe riuer, when nothing hindereth his courſe, hath a ſtill, and as it were, a dead motion; but if you ſeeke
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177216:32"/> to reſtraine or ſtoppe his courſe, he will ſwell and ouerflowe all, now diſdaining, as it were, a bridge: ſo our corruption, when it freely taketh his owne courſe, ſeemeth to be quiet, and as it were dead: but when the commaundement commeth, <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 7. 9.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, as it were to damme it vp, ſinne reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and riſeth againſt it, ſwelling and ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it were, his wonted bankes. In this reſpect, the lawe (ſaith the Maſter of the <note n="u" place="margin">Lib. 3. dist. 40. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sentences) <hi>is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a killing</hi> letter, <hi>becauſe forbidding ſinne, it increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth concupiſcence, and addeth tranſgreſsion vntill grace doe free vs.</hi> But when we are regenerated by the ſpirit of ſanctification, and by the bond of the ſame ſpirit coupled vnto Chriſt; we are freed from this bondage, euen as the wife is freed from the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of her husband by his death. For euen as whileſt we were in the fleſh altogether vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, the lawe, as it were our husband, occaſionally and by accident begot in our ſoules, wholly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with ſinne, euill motions and concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as the fruites and iſſue of our fleſh tending vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death: ſo we being regenerated, and after a ſort dead vnto this corruption, and conſequently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mortified to the law in reſpect of the irritation thereof, and the lawe in that regard dead vnto vs, the ſpirit of Chriſt, who hath vnited vs vnto him as our ſecond husband, begetteth good motions in vs as the fruites of the ſpirit, acceptable vnto God. This is that which the Apoſtle teacheth, <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 7. 1. &amp;c.</note> Rom. 7. for hauing ſaid chap. 6. 14. that ſinne ſhall not haue dominion ouer vs, becauſe we are not vnder the lawe but vnder grace, after he had anſwered an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177216:33"/> and preuented the abuſe of this doctrine, which carnall men would make thereof, as though they might ſin freely, becauſe they are not vnder the law: in the beginning of the ſeuenth chapter he proueth, that we are not vnder the Law, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace, by that ſimilitude which euen now I mentioned: becauſe being regenerated and dead vnto ſin, we are mortified to the Law, and the Law to vs in reſpect of the irritation thereof, cauſed by our corruption; and conſequently are deliuered from the power of it, as a wife is freed from the dominion of her husband, when he is dead.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in our ſanctification wee are freed <note place="margin">Freedome from the terror or coaction of the Law.</note> from the coaction and terror of the Law, breeding ſeruile feare in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnregenerate; wherby, as bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or gally-ſlaues by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whip, they are enforced to the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſome outward duties, which otherwiſe they are vnwilling to do. For thoſe who are vnder the Law, as all men are by nature, are like bond-ſlaues; who for auoiding of puniſhment, are by terror drawne to do ſome forced ſeruice, which is ſo much the more vnwilling, becauſe they looke for no reward. This in the Scriptures is called ſometimes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8. 15.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit of bondage,</hi> and ſometimes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="y" place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit of feare,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we are deliuered, when we receiue the ſpirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and ſanctification; whereby we are ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to worſhip God in holines and righteouſnes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without ſeruile feare,</hi> according to the couenant of grace made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Luk. 1. <note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 1. 74.</note> And in this ſenſe it is ſaid, that the <hi>Law</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>is not impoſed on the iust;</hi> to whom, being as it were a law vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177216:33"/> &amp; willingly performing that which is right, the terror and coaction of the Law, ſo farre forth as they are regenerate, is needleſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as we are freed from the coaction and <note place="margin">Freedome from the rigour or exaction of the Law.</note> terror of the Law, ſo alſo from the exaction and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Law, which they call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which though it be a libertie of ſanctification, and apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to our new obedience; yet it dependeth on the libertie of iuſtification. For as there wee were freed from the Lawes exaction of inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, to the acceptation of our perſons: ſo heere we are freed from the Lawes exaction of perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, to the acceptation of our actions. So that whereas the law condemneth euery the leaſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection or defect, not agreeing with that perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of iuſtice, which it preſcribeth, as a ſin, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and pronounceth the partie in whom that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or imperfection is, accurſed: notwithſtanding the new obedience of Gods children, wrought in them by the Spirit of God, and performed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of grace receiued; though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue in it ſelf, and ſtained with the fleſh, is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God; who couereth their imperfections with the perfect obedience of Chriſt, and not ſo much reſpecteth the perfection of the outward act, which he doth not expect from ſuch weakneſſe, as the integritie of the heart, the vprightneſſe of the wil and deſire, the ſinceritie of the indeuor; which, if it be not wanting, the Lord <note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 8. 12.</note> accepteth the will for the deed, and true endeuour ſtriuing <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 3. 14. 15</note> towards perfection, for the perfect performance. In which reſpect, the Lord, according to his gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177216:34"/>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Malac. 3. 17. Pſal. 103. 13.</note> 
               <hi>vſeth clemencie towards vs, as a tender father vſeth clemencie towards his ſonne,</hi> taking in good part the childiſh endeauour of his children, proceeding from an vnfained deſire to pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>But our libertie in ſanctification is not onely an <note place="margin">§. 17. The libertie of ſanctification as it is a right, with the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof.</note> immunitie, but alſo an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or right, conſiſting of great priuiledges. For, firſt we are not only freed in part from the corruption of ſinne, which wee call mortification; but are alſo poſitiuely made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, being, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers <note n="e" place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 4.</note> of the diuine nature, in that flying from the corruption which is in the world by luſt, we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued according to the <note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 24.</note> image of God, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe. For as the ſacred oyle being powred on the head of <note n="g" place="margin">Pſalm. 133.</note> 
               <hi>Aaron,</hi> (who was a type of Chriſt) diſtilled vnto his lower parts: ſo the <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 45 8.</note> oyle of grace wherewith Chriſt our head was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed <note n="i" place="margin">John 3. 34.</note> without meaſure, is deriued euen to his inferiour members heere on earth, who are alſo therewith <note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor. 1. 21.</note> anointed, <note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 2. 20. 27. Iohn 1. 16.</note> receiuing of his fulneſſe, euen grace for grace. Neither are wee onely freed from the ſeruitude of ſin, Satan, and the world, but in Chriſt our King, who hath ouercome <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 16. 33. Coloſſ. 2. 15.</note> the world, and triumphed ouer ſin and Satan, we are alſo made Kings <note n="n" place="margin">Apocal. 1. 6. Rom 16. 20. 2. Cor. 2. 14. Rom. 8. 37.</note>, with aſſurance to be conquerers of all the enemies of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>And as touching the Law, we are not only freed from the irritation thereof, whereunto our owne corruption did make vs ſubiect, as vnto a husband, who begot foule iſſue of vs tending to death, and ſo left at large: but we are alſo ioyned to another husband which is Chriſt, by his Spirit, whereby
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177216:34"/>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 7. 4.</note> he produceth in vs the fruits of the ſpirit, to the glorie of God. Neither doth the law onely ceaſe to prouoke vs vnto ſin; but, when we are once ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, it becommeth, as <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 24.</note> ſpeaketh, a counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour vnto vs, and a directour vnto good things.</p>
            <p>Neither are wee freed onely from the ſpirit of bondage and feare, but are alſo indued with the ſpirit of libertie and grace, the ſpirit <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 8. 15.</note> of adoption, the ſpirit of <note n="r" place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 7.</note> power, and of loue, and of ſobrietie: which ſpirit hauing ſhed <note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 5. 5.</note> abroad the loue of God in our hearts, teſtifying vnto vs our adoption, and as an <note n="t" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 14.</note> earneſt aſſuring vs of our inheritance, and enflaming our harts with a reciprocal loue of God, and of our neighbour for his ſake: we begin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 7. 22. Pſal. 1. 2. 119. 24</note> in the law of God, as concerning the inner man, neither are the Commandemens of God <note n="*" place="margin">1. Iohn 5. 3.</note> grieuous vnto vs, and we begin to ſerue the Lord not onely without feare, but alſo with <note n="x" place="margin">1. Chron. 28. 9</note> willing minds and vpright harts. For thoſe who are redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſanctified by Chriſt, are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 110. 3.</note> 
               <hi>a people of willingneſſe,</hi> a <note n="z" place="margin">Titus 2. 14.</note> a people peculiar to himſelfe, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good workes.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, concerning the rigour of the Law; we haue not only this immunitie, that the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of our ſincere obedience are not imputed vnto vs; but alſo this priuiledge, that our imperfect obedience, which in it ſelfe is worthie to be reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, notwithſtanding is both accepted of God, and rewarded. For Chriſt hauing waſhed vs with his blood, and ſanctified vs by his Spirit, hath made vs both kings, as I ſaid before, and alſo <note n="a" place="margin">Apocal. 1. 6.</note> Prieſts, or as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, <note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>a royall and holy Prieſthood, to offer</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:177216:35"/> 
               <hi>ſpirituall ſacrifices acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> the ſacrifice of obedience whereby we offer our ſelues <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 12. 1.</note> 
               <hi>as a liuelie, holy and acceptable ſacrifice vnto God, which is our reaſonable ſeruice:</hi> the ſacrifice of almes, whereby we offer our goods, with which <note n="d" place="margin">Hebr. 13. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces God is well pleaſed:</hi> the ſacrifice of a broken and contrite heart <note n="e" place="margin">Pſalm. 51. 19.</note> which is to God in ſtead of all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: the ſacrifice of prayer, which is accepted <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 141. 2.</note> as incenſe, and as the euening ſacrifice: the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of praiſe, that is, the <note n="g" place="margin">Hebr. 13. 15.</note> fruit, or as <hi>Hoſea</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Hoſ. 14. 3.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, the calues of our lips, which the Lord prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 50. 13. 14. 23.</note> before the ſacrifices of goats and bulles: all which, though in themſelues defectiue and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, are notwithſtanding acceptable vnto God, through the mediation of Chriſt; who, making interceſſion for vs, perfumeth <note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 8. 3. 4.</note> al theſe ſacrifices of ours, with the odours of his owne ſacrifice, that ſo they may bee acceptable, and ſweete ſmelling ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours vnto God.</p>
            <p>Neither are they only accepted, but alſo rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For our <note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 11. 18. Pſal. 19. 11.</note> obedience, our <note n="b" place="margin">Hebr. 10. 35. James 1. 12.</note> confidence, our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, our <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 6. 4. 6. 18.</note> prayer, faſting, almes, and <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 6. 35.</note> charitable deeds haue their rewards, in ſo much that <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 10. 42.</note> a cup of cold water giuen in charitie, ſhall not loſe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. In reſpect whereof, wee may well ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 62. 13.</note> 
               <hi>vnto thee Lord, mercie: for thou rewardeſt a man according to his worke.</hi> Which plainly proueth, that the reward of our obedience is not to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the merit of our workes, (which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues cannot ſtand in iudgement) but to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in Chriſt. For there is great mercie in not imputing vnto vs the imperfections of our <pb n="63" facs="tcp:177216:35"/> works; greater, in accepting of them as if they were perfect; but greateſt of all in rewarding them. The conſideration wherof, ought to animate and ſtirre vs vp with willing and cheerefull minds, to obey God, to ſerue him, to call vpon him, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch duties as he requireth of vs; becauſe we are to be aſſured, that hee doth not impute vnto vs our wants, but accept our imperfect obedience, and not only fauourablie accept it, but alſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly reward it.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue ſpoken of the common liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Chriſtians: which being (as we haue heard) <note place="margin">§. 18. The ſpeciall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or that which is peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnder the Gospell.</note> conferred vpon vs in our vocation, iuſtification, and ſanctification; wee are to be exhorted to giue all diligence, both that we may be called, iuſtified, and ſanctified, and alſo that our calling, iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſanctification may be made ſure vnto vs, by leading a godly life. For if we be not ſanctified, nor iuſtified, nor called, then are we (whatſoeuer wee are, rich or poore, noble or baſe, learned or vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) the moſt miſerable bondſlaues of ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; and being ſeruants, howſoeuer for a time wee retaine a place in the houſe of God, yet wee ſhall not abide for euer, but when the time of ſeparation commeth, we ſhall be caſt out: whereas contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being made free by our calling, iuſtification and ſanctification, as the ſonnes of God, wee ſhall haue the priuiledge of ſonnes, which is, <note n="g" place="margin">John 8. 35.</note> to abide in the houſe of God for euer.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the Chriſtian libertie, which is peculiar to the faithfull vnder the Goſpell. For the faithfull vnder the old Teſtament, though they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177216:36"/> were ſons and heires, and therfore enioyed the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer liberties by Chriſt, in whom they beleeued: notwithſtanding vntill the fulneſſe of time came, which was the full age of the Church, they were vnder yeeres; and therefore as ſons, during their minoritie, were ſubiect to <note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 4. 1. &amp;c. &amp; 3. 24.</note> ſchoolemaſters &amp; Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, wherby are meant the pedagogie and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the typicall Church of the Iewes, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ceremoniall and iudiciall lawes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> in which regard, they, though ſonnes, ſeemed little to differ from ſeruants. Both theſe lawes were appendices of the law morall: the ceremoniall, of the firſt table, determining the particulars of that peculiar worſhip which he preſcribed to the typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Church, vntill the comming of Chriſt. The iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, of the ſecond, determining the particulars of that peculiar policie which hee preſcribed to the Commonwealth of the Iewes. So that the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, were the Eccleſiaſticall lawes of that Church; the iudiciall, the ciuill lawes of that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Both were yokes of bondage, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh <note n="i" place="margin">Galath. 5. 1.</note> in reſpect of the Iewes, on whoſe conſciences theſe lawes were impoſed, binding them to the ſtrict obſeruation thereof; in regard whereof, they are called an <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 15. 10.</note> vnſupportable yoke, vnder which notwithſtanding, the faithfull were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="l" place="margin">Galath. 4. 3.</note> 
               <hi>held in bondage.</hi> And as touching the Gentiles, they were as a <note n="m" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 14.</note> wall of ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and the Iewes, and as the doore of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, excluding all from ſaluation that were not of that Church, either as borne Iewes, or as proſelytes. For the reſt were <note n="n" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>without Chriſt, aliants</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:177216:36"/> 
               <hi>from the Commonwealth of Iſrael, ſtrangers from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of promiſe, hauing no hope, liuing without God in the world.</hi> This wal of partitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 14. &amp;c.</note> our Sauiour Chriſt by his death hath diſſolued, taking away all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 15. 9.</note> betweene Iewes and Gentiles, freeing and exempting, both the one and the other, from the obedience both of the iudiciall and ceremoniall law, which were giuen to put a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene the Iewes and the Gentiles, vntill the fulneſſe of time, <note n="q" place="margin">Galath. 4. 4.</note> Gal. 4. 4. the time <note n="r" place="margin">Hebr. 9. 10.</note> of reformation, that is, vntill the comming of the Meſſias, by whoſe death they were to bee <note n="s" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 11. 13.</note> abrogated. For howſoeuer the faithfull, before the Church came to full age, were in bondage vnder the ceremonial, and iudicial law, as vnder ſcholemaſters and Tutors; yet, when <note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 4. 3. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>the fulneſſe of time came, God ſent his Sonne borne of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and borne vnder the Law, that he might redeeme them that were vnder the law:</hi> meaning that wee are redeemed, not only from the morall law, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects before named; but alſo from the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and iudiciall, euen in reſpect of obedience.</p>
            <p>For as touching the ceremoniall law, as it was an <note n="u" place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. 14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epheſ. 2. 15.</note> hand-writing of ordinances which was (though vnderhand) againſt vs; Chriſt hath cancelled it, and nailed it to his croſſe. As it was a <note n="*" place="margin">Hebr. 10. 1. Coloſſ. 2. 17. John 1. 17.</note> ſhadow and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of things to come, Chriſt hath aboliſhed it, by performing that indeed, which it did but ſhadow and prefigure: for the law was giuen by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but grace and truth by Chriſt. For as grace is oppoſed to the curſe, ſo truth to figures: the ceremonies therefore of the law gaue place as ſhadowes to the bodie, and as figures to the truth.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:177216:37"/>
            <p>The ciuill or iudiciall law, being the poſitiue lawes of that people, Chriſt abrogated, when ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the propheſie of <hi>Daniel</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Dan. 9. 26. 27</note>, he deſtroying the Commonwealth of the Iewes, their citie and temple, did withall aboliſh their policie and lawes. For the very citie, temple, and whole ſtate of the Iewes, being types and ſhadowes of Chriſt and his Church, were, when Chriſt was exhibited, and his vniuerſall Church by preaching the Goſpell to all nations, planted <note n="y" place="margin">Matth. 24. 14</note>, to giue place; and with them, their lawes, which were to hold but till the fulneſſe of time. For as the Apoſtle ſaith, the Prieſthood (namely of <hi>Aaron)</hi> being tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated, <note n="z" place="margin">Hebr. 7. 12.</note> the law (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Moſes)</hi> is alſo tranſlated.</p>
            <p>Howbeit there is ſome difference betweene the abrogating of the Ceremoniall, and of the Iudicial law: the ceremonial rites, becauſe they were princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ordained to prefigure Chriſt, are ſo aboliſhed, that it is not lawful for Chriſtians to obſerue them, for that were to deny that Chriſt is come. <hi>Ea no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant Chriſtiani</hi> (ſaith <note n="a" place="margin">Contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Manich. lib. 19. cap. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine) per quae Chriſtus promittebatur; nec adhuc promittuntur, quia iam imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt: Chriſtians do not obſerue thoſe things, by which Chriſt was promiſed; neither are they ſtill promiſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are alreadie fulfilled.</hi> The iudiciall ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe they principally tended to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of iuſtice and equitie, may be vſed, ſo they be not impoſed or obſerued by vertue of the iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall law: for that were, though indirectly, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that the Meſſias is alreadie come. Both lawes were dead with Chriſt, though they were not bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, but as it were kept aboue ground, euen by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177216:37"/> Chriſtians among the Iewes, vntill the diſſolution of the temple and citie of Ieruſalem. After which time, the ceremonial precepts were not only dead, as <note n="b" place="margin">Tho. 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, quaest. 104. 3. cap.</note> one ſaith, but alſo deadly to the obſeruers of them; but the iudicials not ſo.</p>
            <p>Now, this Chriſtian libertie, as it is an immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is a freedome from all bond of conſcience, in <note place="margin">§. 19. Peculiar Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie, as it is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie.</note> reſpect of outward things, which are neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded nor forbidden in the eternall law of God. Of which there are two ſorts, the ordinances of men concerning things indifferent, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God.</p>
            <p>For as touching the former, ſeeing there is no law that bindeth the conſcience properly, but only the law of God, in which ſenſe hee is called <note n="c" place="margin">James 4. 12.</note> our only Law-giuer, &amp; ſeeing we are freed from thoſe lawes of God, which determined thoſe particulars, which are neither commanded nor forbidden in the moral law of God: it is plaine therfore, that our conſcience is free in reſpect of theſe things. As for the lawes of men, whether they be eccleſiaſticall or ciuill, they do not properly bind the conſcience; becauſe neither is ſimple obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce due vnto them, neither can they make any particular, which in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the morall law, is indifferent, as being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commanded nor forbidden, to be ſimplie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of a Chriſtian is exempted from humane power, and cannot bee bound, but where God doth bind it. And therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, as he chargeth the Corinthians, that, ſeeing they were <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 23.</note> bought with a price, they ſhould not be the ſeruants of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (which is not to be vnderſtood
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177216:38"/> of externall ſeruitude, but of the bondage of the conſcience) and likewiſe the Coloſſians, <note n="c" place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. 16.</note> that <hi>no man ſhould condemne them,</hi> (that is, take vpon him to bind the conſcience with guilt of ſin) <hi>in reſpect of meate and drinke, or holy daies:</hi> ſo he reproueth the <note n="f" place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. 20. 21. 22.</note> Coloſſians, for obſeruing the traditions of men, with opinion of neceſſitie, as if the conſcience were bound by them, or religion were to be placed in them.</p>
            <p>Herein therfore the Church of Rome is alſo an enemie to Chriſtian liberty, not only in burdening Chriſtians with an heape of innumerable traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ceremonies; but chiefely, in impoſing them vpon the conſcience: teaching, that the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church are with like <note n="g" place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 4.</note> reuerence, and equall affection of pietie to be receiued, as the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God; and that the commandements of the Church, euen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning outward things, do bind the conſcience. And although many of their ceremonies be wicked; more, ridiculous; moſt of them, ſuperfluous; yet ſo abſurd they are, as to impoſe them to be obſerued, not only with opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of neceſſitie, as binding the conſcience, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of worſhip, of perfection, of merit, of ſpirituall efficacie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by this libertie we are freed from ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſitie of conſcience, in reſpect of the creatures, which are ordained for our vſe; the difference of cleane and vncleane (which was made by the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall law) being taken away. <hi>Nothing,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 15. 11.</note> 
               <hi>that goeth into the mouth, defileth a man.</hi> And <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 14. 14.</note> 
               <hi>I know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and am perſwaded</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:177216:38"/> 
               <hi>by the Lord leſus, that there is nothing common or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane of it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this libertie is not only an immunitie, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or power, both in reſpect of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances <note place="margin">§. 20. Peculiar Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie, as it is a right.</note> of men, and alſo of the creatures of God. For, being freed from the ceremoniall, and iudicial lawes of God, and therefore not tied to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular or certaine lawes, which ſhould determine the particulars not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in the word of God: hereupon ariſeth a liberty, both to Law-giuers, and thoſe who are ſubiect to lawes. The Law-giuers are not reſtrained to any particulars, but haue libertie to ordaine ſuch holſome, either conſtitutions Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, or lawes ciuill, as are not repugnant to the word of God. Lawes there muſt be, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the particulars not mentioned in the generall law of God: for they are the very bond of humane ſocieties, neceſſarie for the execution of the lawes of God, and for the maintenance of peace and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der among men. Neither can it be denied, but that as the iudiciall law being aboliſhed, it is lawfull for Law-giuers to ordaine ciuill lawes; ſo likewiſe the ceremonial law being abrogated, to eſtabliſh lawes Eccleſiaſticall. Only the queſtion is, who muſt bee theſe Law-giuers. Surely, not the Presbyteries of euery pariſh, which neuer were in vſe in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, but Synodes; as appeareth by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall practiſe of the Church, both in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, and euer ſince. Synodes, I ſay, either prouinciall, or nationall; and thoſe aſſembled, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of ſome one nation, or out of ſome more then one, which ſome call <hi>Concilia media,</hi> or laſtly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177216:39"/> generall. The authoritie of Synodes prouinciall and nationall hath alwaies been of great regard, though there wanted a Chriſtian Magiſtrate to ſecond and confirme them, being both aſſembled and moderated by the authoritie of Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes and Archbiſhops: but when both nationall Synodes are aſſembled, and the Synodall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ratified by the authoritie of the Soueraigne, and that according to the poſitiue lawes of the land, authorizing him ſo to doe; I ſee not, why men ſhould not as well thinke themſelues bound to obſerue lawes Eccleſiaſticall, as Ciuill. For though ſome make a difference betweene them in this behalfe, becauſe ciuill lawes determining particulars belonging to the ſecond table, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be violated without breaking the ſecond table, whereas eccleſiaſticall lawes determining particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars appertaining to the firſt table, may be broken without tranſgreſſing of the firſt table; yet, who ſeeth not the weakenes of this diſtinction? Seeing the ſecond table is broken by diſobeying the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authoritie of ſuperiours (which wee ought to obey for conſcience ſake) as well by tranſgreſſing the one, as the other. Superiours in the Church are to be honoured and obeied by the fifth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and other Scriptures <note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 13. 17.</note>, as well as ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, in the common-wealth. And if their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, when they wanted the concurrence of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, were of force in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Primitiue Church; then much greater is their validitie, being confirmed by the authoritie of the Soueraigne, and the Soueraigne authorized thereunto by law.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177216:39"/>
            <p>The freedome of the ſubiect is, that being freed from the yoke of the iudiciall and ceremonial law, hee may with a free conſcience obey any other lawes whether Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill, which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not diſſonant from the word of God, are or ſhall be impoſed vpon him. Which, though it be a plaine and euident truth, yet by ſome men it is not obſerued.</p>
            <p>And as touching the vſe of the creatures, and of al things indifferent, we are to know, that the right and dominion wee had ouer the creatures, which was loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> is reſtored in Chriſt, (for all are yours, ſaith the Apoſtle <note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 22.</note>, and you are Chriſts) and that not onely for Chriſtians vnder the Goſpell, but alſo for all the faithfull from the beginning. For we reade, Gen. 9. <note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 9. 2. 3.</note>, that to <hi>Noah,</hi> who was the heire <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 11. 7.</note> of the righteouſnes, which is by faith, the graunt was renewed, and free vſe of the creatures permitted. Howbeit this freedome was by the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall law reſtrained, not only after the giuing of the law by <hi>Moſes;</hi> but alſo before, a difference being put <note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 7. 2. 9. 4.</note> betweene things cleane and vncleane: which difference by Chriſt is taken away. For, no <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 14. 14.</note> creature is vncleane of it ſelfe, but euery <note n="r" place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 4.</note> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is good, and nothing to be refuſed, but may be receiued with thankſgiuing. Yea of all outward things, not forbidden of God, which commonly are called things in different, the Apoſtle affirmeth in generall, that <note n="s" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 12.</note> 
               <hi>all things are lawfull,</hi> and <note n="t" place="margin">Tit. 1. 15.</note> 
               <hi>to the pure all things are pure.</hi> By this libertie therefore the faithfull are priuiledged, with freedome of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to vſe or forbeare any of the creatures of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177216:40"/> God created for our vſe, or things in different, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out opinion of neceſſitie to bee brought <note n="u" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 12.</note> vnder the power thereof, or placing religion therein. In which reſpect, <hi>Baſil</hi> fitly calleth things indifferent, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things in our power, or left to our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</p>
            <p>But here, for auoiding of error, three things are <note place="margin">§. 21. Application of the generall doctrine to this particular.</note> from the generall doctrine to be repeated. Firſt, that this alſo is a libertie of the ſonnes of God: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that it is ſpirituall: and thirdly, that it is a true libertie. For as touching the firſt; though all <note place="margin">1. That this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is a libertie of the ſonnes of God.</note> things be pure to the pure; yet <note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 1. 15.</note> 
               <hi>to them that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and vnbeleeuing, nothing is cleane.</hi> Though to <note n="x" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 12. 1. Tim. 4. 3.</note> the faithfull all theſe outward things are lawfull; yet to the wicked and vnbeleeuers nothing is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yea, thoſe actions, which are materially good, as being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded of God, as they proceed from them, are turned into ſinne. Which is ſpoken, not to this end, to driue men into deſperate courſes; but to force them, without further delaies, to break off the courſe of their ſinnes by ſpeedie and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentance, and to ſue vnto God for mercie and pardon in Chriſt; becauſe this is the only thing which they may lawfully doe and without ſinne, and which vntill they doe, they doe nothing elſe but ſinne, and by ſinne hoord vp wrath againſt the day of wrath, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, though this libertie concerne out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">2. That this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is a ſpirituall libertie.</note> things; yet it ſelfe is inward and ſpirituall, as being a libertie of the conſcience. Now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience reſpecteth God, as our outward actions and the externall fruits of our conſcience reſpect men;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177216:40"/> men; who may moderate or reſtraine the externall actions, wherein the outward vſe of our libertie conſiſteth; the inward libertie notwithſtanding of the conſcience before God, remaining entire. <hi>They greatly erre,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caluin, who thinke that their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jnstit. lib. 3. cap. 19. §. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Christian libertie is nothing, vnleſſe they vſe it before men. But they ought to thinke, that by their libertie they obtaine no new thing in the ſight of men, but before God; and that their libertie conſisteth as well in abstaining, as vſing. If they know, that it is a thing indifferent before God, whether they eate fleſh or egges, put on red or blacke apparell: it is enough, and more then enough. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is now looſe, whereto the benefit of this libertie doth appertaine: therefore, though hereafter they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from fleſh all their life, and alwaies weare one co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; they are neuer the leſſe free. Yea therefore becauſe they are free, they doe with a free conſcience abstaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, as this libertie is ſpirituall, ſo alſo a true <note place="margin">3. That this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is a true li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</note> libertie. Now all true and lawfull libertie of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is limited and bounded: the libertie of the Creator alone, being vncircumſcribed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any arrogate to themſelues an vnbounded libertie, it is a licentiouſneſſe, and not a true liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. As firſt, in regard of lawes and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men; there are bounds ſet, firſt to the lawgiuers, in reſpect both of the things comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and alſo of the manner of commanding. For, lawgiuers may not aſſume vnto them a libertie to commaund what they liſt, but onely ſuch things as they know, not to be repugnant to the law of God. For they muſt know, that al their lawes are limited by the law of God, and themſelues <hi rend="sup">a</hi> vpon paine of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177216:41"/> damnation, reſtrained from commaunding that which God forbiddeth, and from forbidding that which God commandeth. For by wicked lawes, they make themſelues like <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> who cauſed all Iſrael to ſinne. Moreouer, they muſt be carefull, not onely to command that which is lawfull; but alſo in ciuill lawes, thoſe things which bee expedient, and profitable for the weale publike; and in lawes Eccleſiaſticall, ſuch things as tend <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 26. 40.</note> to decencie, to order, and edification. Otherwiſe, though the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect may lawfully obey, in ſuch caſes; yet the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer offendeth in abuſing his authoritie, which was giuen him for the good of the inferiours.</p>
            <p>Againe, in reſpect of the manner, ſuperiours muſt keepe them within their bounds, and not take vpon them the authoritie of our <note n="c" place="margin">James 4. 12.</note> one only Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer, who hath power to ſaue, and to deſtroy; which is, to bind the conſciences of men, as, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that vpon the conſcience as ſimplie neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which God by his law hath left indifferent; or by teaching <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 15. 2. 9.</note> men to place religion in the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their traditions. For this is the practiſe of the Antichriſt of Rome; who, vſurping the authority of God, and challenging to himſelfe a boundleſſe power, ſitteth in the conſciences of men, as God.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe to the ſubiect; for as he may not think, that hee hath libertie to obey any lawes of men, though vnlawfull, and much leſſe to place religion or perfection in the obſeruation of them, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do: ſo on the other ſide, he may not thinke, that hee hath libertie to breake the lawes of men, though not vnlawfull, and much leſſe to place reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177216:41"/> or perfection therein; as they ſeeme to doe, who vſe to be oppoſite to the Papiſts in the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie extreame. For, I beſeech you, do not many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, thinke themſelues the more religious, for refuſing obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; conformitie to the lawes, and cenſure others as formaliſts and time-ſeruers? But beloued, as we are not to iudge <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 14. 1. 3. &amp;c.</note> thoſe, who out of weakneſſe refuſe conformitie; ſo thoſe which be refractarie, ſhould not thinke, either the better of themſelues for not conforming, or the worſe of others for conforming. The kingdome <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 14. 17.</note> of God doth not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in theſe things. And certainly, if <note n="g" place="margin">Galath. 5. 6. &amp; 6. 15.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumciſion, nor vncircumciſion auaile any thing; then much leſſe the vſe or forbearance of thoſe ceremonies, which are in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie among vs. Doth not the Apoſtle plainly tell vs, <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 8.</note> that theſe outward things doe not commend vs vnto God, and that neither the vſe or forbearance of them in it ſelfe doth make vs either better, or worſe before God? But when they be vſed or forborne with diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to lawfull authoritie, without due regard of auoiding ſcandall, with vncharitable cenſuring and iudging one of another, with alienation of the affection of one brother from another; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there is fault committed. And who ſeeth not, that while contentions grow hotte about theſe things, both charitie and pietie waxeth cold?</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the creatures and things indifferent, though we haue free libertie to vſe or forbeare them; yet it is not a boundleſſe libertie. For the law of God hath ſet it foure bounds, <hi>viz.</hi> pietie, loyaltie, charitie, and ſobrietie. <hi>Pietie,</hi> reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177216:42"/> Gods glorie and worſhip: <hi>Loyaltie,</hi> hauing reference to ſuperiours; <hi>Charitie,</hi> to all men; <hi>Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> to our ſelues. Canſt thou not vſe thy libertie in ſome particular, without Gods diſhonor, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of his ſeruice? Remember, that <hi>whether</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 31.</note> 
               <hi>you eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer you doe, you must do all to the glorie of God.</hi> Cannot thy libertie be vſed, without contempt of the Magiſtrates lawfull authority? Remember, that God hath commanded thee to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey thy ſuperiours in all lawfull things, as <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 12.</note> all things (not forbidden by God) are lawfull; that all <hi>authoritie is</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 13. 1. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>from God,</hi> and that, <hi>hee which reſiſteth lawfull authoritie, reſiſteth God;</hi> that <hi>they which reſiſt, ſhall receiue to themſelues iudgement;</hi> and that thou muſt <hi>obey not only for feare, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> Remember what S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <note n="m" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13. 16.</note> Be ſubiect to all humane ordinance, whether the ſoueraigne, or ſubordinate gouernours. But how? <hi>As free, and not as hauing the libertie for a cloak of naughtines, but as the ſeruants of God.</hi> Can it not be vſed without the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of thy weake brother? <hi>Take heed,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 9. 10. 24. Rom. 14. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>leſt thy libertie be an offence to the weake. For he that ſcandalizeth his brother, ſinneth againſt Chriſt. Wherefore if meate offend my brother, I will not eat fleſh whiles the world ſtandeth, rather then I will offend him.</hi> Laſtly, can it not be vſed in ſome particular, vnleſſe thou ſhalt paſſe the bounds of ſobrietie, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, humilitie, modeſtie, frugalitie, &amp;c? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what the Apoſtle ſaith, <note n="o" place="margin">Galath. 5. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Brethren you are called to libertie, only vſe not your libertie as an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here ariſeth a doubtful queſtion, the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <note place="margin">§. 22. Deciſion of a doubtfull que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, what is to be done, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſeeme to be in a ſtrait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Magiſtrate, and offence to the weake.</note>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177216:42"/> wherof is needful for theſe times. For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there ſeemeth to be a conflict betweene the law of loyaltie, and the law of charitie; as when that which the Magiſtrate commandeth, cannot (as we thinke) be obſerued without the offence or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the weake. In which caſe of Antiomie (which ſome ſay is our caſe) diuers know not which way to turne them, and others erroneouſlie chuſe to diſobey the Magiſtrate, rather then ſeeme to offend their weake brethren.</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore vprightly what I ſhall ſay, and the Lord giue you vnderſtanding minds, and tractable hearts, to ſee and embrace the truth.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore vnderſtand, that we are neuer caſt into ſuch an exigent betweene two ſinnes not yet committed; but there is an iſſue from them both without a third. Suppoſe therfore, that in this caſe there were an Antinomie, or ſuch an oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two lawes of loyalty &amp; charity, as that the one could not be obſerued, without the neglect of the other. In ſuch caſes of Antinomie, we are to know, that if wee obey the ſuperiour law, vnto which we are more bound, as hauing higher and more principal ends; the inferiour <note n="p" place="margin">Matth. 12. 7. Jerem. 7. 22. Luke 14. 26.</note> (which giueth place vnto it) is not broken. Now, the ſupreme end is the glorie of God; then, the common ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church; then, euery mans owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; then, the ſaluation of his neighbour; then, the common outward good of the Church, or Commonwealth; then, our owne; then, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. So that publike and common goods are to be preferred before priuate, &amp; ſpiritual before cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177216:43"/> and the glorie of God before all. Well then, thou ſayeſt thou mayeſt not yeeld to the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, as namely, the Surplice, the Croſſe, and knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at Communion; becauſe theſe things cannot be done without ſcandalizing of thy brother. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it were ſo, and remember that I doe but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it. But on the other ſide, thou refuſing the vſe of indifferent things, whereunto thy Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie extendeth, being enioyned by lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, with ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions as theſe are enioyned; I ſay vnto thee without ſuppoſition, that beſides thy diſobeying the lawfull authoritie of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, and of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, whom thou oughteſt to obey euen for conſcience ſake; thou doeſt ſcandalize, firſt, thy weake brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affected as thy ſelfe, who by thine example, for which thou perhaps thinkeſt thou haſt good ground, are animated, or, as the Apoſtle <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 10.</note> ſpeaketh, edified, without ground, to contemne <note n="r" place="margin">In this ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall they are deepest, who are of greatest note.</note> the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Magiſtrate, and of the Church; &amp; from that contempt do many of them proceed to miſlike of the State; and from miſlike, either to ſeparation, or to ſome degree of diſloyall diſcontentment. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe of thine owne diſpoſition, thou doeſt offend them who are more loyally affected; who, if they bee not the better grounded in our <note n="s" place="margin">Jud. 20.</note> moſt holy faith, do ſtumble at your practiſe, and begin to ſtagger in the profeſſion and practiſe of religion, when they ſee me ſeeming moſt zealous in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and profeſſing, (as they pretend) the cauſe of ſinceritie, vpon no iuſt cauſe to abandon their miniſterie, to oppoſe themſelues againſt authority,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177216:43"/> to maintaine a faction in the Church, and wilfully (for any thing that they can ſee) to perſiſt in a bad courſe. And hereupon many take occaſion to reſt in outward ciuilitie, without grace, and to miſlike all forwardnes in religion for your ſakes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now heere ſeemeth to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall falling two waies;</hi> indeed a ſingle ſuppoſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, oppoſed to a double ſcandall, ioyned with diſobedience. If no more could be ſaid, who would doubt on which ſide rather to encline? But to theſe Iadde other reſpects, that ought to be regarded more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſuppoſed ſcandall. The queſtion is not, as many would ſeeme to vnderſtand it, whether, it being a thing arbitrarie, and meerely left vnto our owne choice, either to vſe theſe ceremonies, or to forbeare them, (as it was in the Apoſtles queſtion of eating fleſh) whether (I ſay) wee ought to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, if we vnderſtood that a brother would bee offended at the vſe of them, or not: for then there were no queſtion, but that for auoiding of ſcandal, we ought to abſtaine. But theſe things are not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarie, or in our choice; but impoſed by lawfull authoritie, and that with ſuch conditions, as that the obſeruation of theſe things being indifferent in themſelues, becommeth reſpectiuely neceſſarie. Firſt in reſpect of authoritie, which not only for feare, but alſo for conſcience <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note> ſake, we are bound to obey in all lawfull things. This one neceſſitie of obedience is ſufficient to excuſe me from ſcandall, eſpecially if I do my endeuour to preuent it, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be ſhewed. Secondly, in reſpect of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions wherewith they are impoſed; as, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177216:44"/> the Communion vnleſſe we kneele; not to go on in our miniſterie, vnleſſe we conforme. For, care of auoiding ſcandal reſpecteth arbitrarie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and not neceſſary duties appertaining to Gods glory, and our ſaluation: which we muſt performe, though all the world would be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded therat. The care of thine owne ſaluation muſt be preferred to the ſuppoſed danger of another mans fall: the care of the Churches ſaluation, much more: the glorie of God, moſt of all. Well then, mayeſt thou not receiue the Communion, being a dutie appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to thine owne ſaluation, to the edification of the Church, and communion of Saints, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, vnleſſe thou wilt receiue it vpon thy knees? (it being a geſture not only lawfull, but moſt conuenient to be vſed in ſuch a part of Gods worſhip, as is performed with inuocation <note n="*" place="margin">J meane not only prayer, but alſo thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, in regard whereof it is called the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist.</note> on the name of God; eſpecially ſeeing the geſture vſed at meales is not to bee vrged, vnleſſe the Sacrament were with our meales, as at the firſt inſtitution with Chriſts laſt ſupper, and in the primitiue Church with their loue feaſts, receiued; for the cauſe of the geſture being worthily taken away, the <note n="*" place="margin">So the cauſe of ſtanding at the Paſſeouer ceaſſing, the gesture it ſelfe was altered by the Church, and that alteration confirmed by the practiſe of Christ, (who not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding perfectly fuifil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Law.) Luke 22. 14.</note> reaſon of retaining it ceaſſeth; for which cauſe the Councill of <hi>Laodicea, cap.</hi> 28. <note n="*" place="margin">Et Concil. Constantinop. in Trullo. c. 74.</note> as it forbad loue-feaſts in the Church: ſo alſo <hi>accubitus,</hi> the geſture vſed at feaſts.) I ſay vnto thee confidently, if thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not receiue it, vnleſſe thou doeſt kneele; thou oughteſt to receiue it kneeling, though another would be offended thereat.</p>
            <p>Maieſt thou not preach the Word (to omit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the miniſteriall function, the neceſſitie
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177216:44"/> whereof ſhould preuaile with vs more then a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſcandall, for it ſhall ſoffice to inſiſt in this one particular) mayeſt thou not, I ſay, preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt, being a dutie whereof neceſſitie is impoſed vpon thee, and <note n="u" place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 16.</note> Woe bee vnto thee if thou preach not the Goſpell; a dutie wherby thou art bound in eſpecial manner to edifie the Church, and to glorifie God; vnleſſe thou yeeld to the vſe of ſuch things, as are neither in themſelues vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (I meane the Surplice and the Croſſe, whereof the one in the iudgement of the Church ſerueth for decencie, and the other rightly vnderſtood ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to edification), neither as they are vſed in our Church, being neither impoſed nor obſerued with ſuperſtition, or opinion of neceſſitie in themſelues, or of worſhip, as though we placed religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them, and much leſſe with the other popiſh conceits of merit, with which they obſerue all their traditions, or efficacie, which they aſcribe eſpecially to the Croſſe? Thou oughteſt to preferre the glorie of God in the ſaluation of his people by thy miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, before the ſuppoſed, and perhaps but preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſcandall of others.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Yea but</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3. 8.</note> 
               <hi>we may not do euill, that good may come of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The queſtion is of things indifferent. For though we may &amp; muſt obey Magiſtrates, though they be euill; yet we muſt obey neither good nor bad vnto euill. For wee muſt obey, only, in the <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 25.</note> Lord.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>But though the things be indifferent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, yet their vſe may be vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:177216:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, when they be impoſed either with opinion of neceſſitie in themſelues, of religion to be placed in them, of perfection or merit to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by them, (all which conceits our Church deteſteth, as is manifeſt by the doctrine, whereby ceremonies are to be weighed:) or with ſcandall (I do not ſay taken, but) giuen to others</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Yea but it is euill to offend my weake brother, that euill I may not do, that good may come of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwere, in not yeelding to conformitie, thou both diſobeyeſt the Magiſtrate, and offendeſt thy weake brother too. So that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſeemeſt loath to do that which is lawfull and good, for feare of an imagined euill; thou addeſt euill to euill, that is, to diſobedience, ſcandall; and beſides, to the moſt neceſſarie duties of Gods worſhip, preferreſt the auoiding of a ſuppoſed ſcandall.</p>
            <p>For all this while I ſpeak but by ſuppoſition. For here is a ſuppoſall of Antinomie or oppoſition of the two lawes of loyaltie and charitie, as though the one could not be obſerued without the breach of the other; which is not ſo. For where the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate enioyneth the vſe of an indifferent thing, whereat it is feared ſome will take offence; his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, for preuenting the ſcandall, to giue ſome time of information; that the weake may be inſtructed, as touching the indifferencie of the thing, and the ſufficiencie of his authoritie to command it, and of their dutie in ſubmitting themſelues to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation thereof. It is alſo the dutie of the Miniſter, to endeuour to preuent the ſcandall, by informing his hearers, that thoſe things which God hath neither
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177216:45"/> commanded nor forbidden, are things indifferent; that no ſuch thing is vncleane in it ſelfe; that all ſuch things are lawfull, and ſuch as whereunto Chriſtian libertie doth extend; that in all lawfull things the Magiſtrate is to be obeyed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that theſe things being enioyned, they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may, in reſpect of their Chriſtian libertie, with free conſcience vſe them; but alſo muſt, in reſpect of Gods Commandement requiring obedience, yeeld to the obſeruation of them. Which courſe hauing been taken (as it hath among vs) if any will ſtill be offended, it is peeuiſhnes and obſtinacie, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then weakeneſſe; and an offence taken, but not giuen: in which caſe, the law of charitie it ſelfe doth not bind vs: and that, in two reſpects, not yet mentioned. The one, in reſpect of God; the other, in reſpect of his truth. For, I may not offend God, not to offend my brother. And it is Gods truth, that Chriſtian libertie priuiledgeth both Chriſtian Lawgiuers (with ſuch cautions as before haue bin mentioned) to ordaine ſuch lawes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, as they ſhall iudge expedient: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſubiects, without ſcrupuloſitie of conſcience to obſerue them. Now, it is a principle, <hi>Satius est naſci ſcandalum quam deſeri verum: It is better a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall ſhould ariſe, then the truth to be forſaken or betrayed.</hi> Is our Chriſtian libertie in this point called into queſtion, whether Magiſtrates may command ſuch things, and whether ſubiects may obey? we muſt maintaine our libertie, though others would be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thereat. The Apoſtles, though for a time they yeelded much to the weakneſſe of the Iewes,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:177216:46"/> doing and forbearing many things, to auoid their offence; yet when their libertie <note n="x" place="margin">Galath. 2. 3. 4</note> was called into queſtion, they reſolutely maintained it, not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their offence. And when as by <hi>Peters</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himſelfe from the Gentiles, for feare of offending the Iewes, the libertie of Chriſtians was called into queſtion; <note n="y" place="margin">Galath. 2. 11. 12. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to his face, and reproued him before them all, as hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the profeſſion of the Goſpell. And ſo muſt they be content to be vſed, who follow <hi>Peters</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in this behalfe. Thus much by the way to perſwade the people to obedience and loyalty, and the Miniſters to conformitie; which I beſeech God to effect for his Chriſts ſake.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus premiſed concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">§. 23. Obiections con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an libertie in outward things anſwered.</note> and qualitie of this peculiar libertie of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; it will not be hard to anſwere the obiections of thoſe, who runne into contrarie extreames con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> 1. For firſt, on the one ſide, it is obiected; that ſeeing Chriſt hath ſet vs free co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning things indifferent, no man ought to reſtraine vs; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the lawes commaunding or forbidding the vſe of indifferent things, are againſt Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwere, firſt: that Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie is wholly ſpirituall, being a libertie of the conſcience and inner man, which may ſtand with the outward ſeruitude of <note n="z" place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 22.</note> bondſlaues, much more with the ſubiection and obedience of free ſubiects. For though the outward vſe of the libertie be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated by the Magiſtrate, and confined; yet the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177216:46"/> inward libertie of the conſcience is not impaired, ſo long as the ſubiect may obey with free conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before God; that is, ſo long as the Magiſtrate ſeeketh not to bind the conſcience, and to impoſe things not commanded of God as neceſſarie in themſelues, and as matters of religion before God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the liberty of Chriſtians is a true, and therefore not an vnbounded libertie. Now, one of the bounds and limits which God hath ſet it, is, as you haue heard, the law of loyaltie, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring obedience to ſuperiours. Wherefore a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, though in reſpect of the inward man he be free, as being the ſonne of God by adoption in Chriſt; yet in reſpect of the outward man, hee ought to be a ſeruant, not only to his <note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 13. 16</note> ſuperiours, in loyaltie and obedience; but alſo to <note n="b" place="margin">Galath. 5. 13. 1. Cor. 9. 19. &amp;c.</note> all, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence and charitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> 2 On the other ſide, it is obiected. 1. That for conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note> ſake we are to obey the Magiſtrate; that is, that we are bound in conſcience ſo to doe; therefore the lawes and commandements of the Magiſtrate do bind the conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It followes not, for although we are bound in conſcience, to obey the lawfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements and lawes of ſuperiours; yet that bond is not in the particular lawes of men, but in the generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> 3. Againe: A thing indifferent enioyned by the Magiſtrate, becommeth neceſſarie, <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note> for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is neceſſarie that you be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: therefore the commandement of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177216:47"/> doth binde the conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither doth this follow. For it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neceſſary, not by the particular commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of man, but by the generall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. For, notwithſtanding the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Magiſtrate, the thing commanded remaineth indifferent in it ſelfe, and before God; and ſo to bee vſed with free conſcience, without placing any religion therein; howſoeuer it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth neceſſarie ſo farre forth as by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall commandement of God, I am bound thereto. And this is that which <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 16.</note> ſaith, that we muſt obey Magiſtrates, <hi>as free,</hi> and yet <hi>as the ſeruants of God.</hi> Free, in reſpect of our conſciences exempted from humane power; and yet as ſeruants of God, bound in conſcience to obey him in obeying them, ſo farre forth as he doth commaund vs to obey them.</p>
            <p>The truth of theſe anſweres ſhall not onely be demonſtrated as it were before your eyes by a fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme, wherein is concluded the bond of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and neceſſitie of dutie in obeying the commaundements of men, but alſo by other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons proued.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Syllogiſme:</head>
               <item>All lawfull commaundements of Magiſtrates thou art bound in conſcience by the lawe of God to obey, ſo farre forth as he requireth ſuch commaundements to be obeyed:</item>
               <item>This or that particular is a lawfull commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Magiſtrate:</item>
               <item>Therefore this or that particular thou art bound
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177216:47"/> in conſcience by the law of God to obey, ſo farre forth as God requireth ſuch commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements to be obeyed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By which argumentation wee may conceiue, that the diſtinction of neceſſitie vſed in ſchooles, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is <hi>neceſsitas conſequentis,</hi> which is ſimple or abſolute, &amp; <hi>neceſsitas conſequentiae,</hi> which is not ſimple, but vpon condition of other things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed, may not vnfitly be applied to the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of duetie impoſed by the lawes, either of God, or man. For Gods commandement impoſeth the neceſſitie as it were of the conſequent, (without preſuppoſing other things) requiring ſimple and abſolute obedience. The lawe of man doth not impoſe the neceſſitie of the conſequent, or require ſimple obedience; but it impoſeth onely a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the conſequence, that is, ſuch a neceſſitie and no other, as may ſoundly be concluded from the lawe of God, and ſo farre forth as it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded thence. Or to ſpeake more plainely: in a ſimple ſentence without interpoſing any conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or preſuppoſing any antecedent whereupon it is to be inferred, I may ſay, either particularly <hi>this commaundement of God is neceſſarily, or by neceſsitie of dutie to be obeyed;</hi> or generally, <hi>all Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are neceſſarily to be obſerued.</hi> And this ſpeech is of neceſſary truth. But concerning mens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, if I ſhall ſay in the generall, <hi>All the commaundements of men are neceſſarily to be obſerued,</hi> the ſpeech will be falſe and abſurd: if in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, <hi>this commaundement of the Magistrate is neceſſarily to be obſerued:</hi> this ſpeech cannot bee neceſſarie
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:177216:48"/> ſimply, or by the neceſſitie of the conſequent, or (to ſpeake more plainely for the explicating of that phraſe) by the neceſſitie of a ſimple ſentence, wherein the conſequent (or predicat) is both ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and neceſſarily affirmed of the antecedent or ſubiect; it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, I ſay, be ſimply neceſſarie, becauſe (as you heard) the generall is falſe. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if you preſuppoſe theſe two things: firſt, that all lawfull commaundements of Magiſtrates are by the commaundement of God neceſſarily to be obſerued, ſo farre forth as he commaundeth them to be obſerued: ſecondly, that this particular is a lawfull commaundement of the Magiſtrate; vpon theſe premiſes you may prooue that ſpeech to be true by neceſſitie of conſequence, <hi>viz.</hi> that this particular commaundement of the Magiſtrate is neceſſarily to be obſerued, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſome ſophiſter will obiect, that I might as well conclude thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ.</hi> All lawfull commaundements of the Magiſtrate muſt neceſſarily be obeyed:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſs.</hi> This or that particular is a lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Magiſtrate:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concl.</hi> Therefore neceſſarily to be obeyed.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that the propoſition of this ſyllogiſme needeth proofe, as not being manifeſt of it ſelfe. You will ſay, it may thus be prooued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſ.</hi> What is commaunded of God, muſt neceſſarily be performed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſs.</hi> Obedience to all lawfull commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Magiſtrates is commaunded of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concl.</hi> Therefore obedience to all lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:177216:48"/> of Magiſtrates, is neceſſarily to be performed.</p>
            <p>But I ſay againe the aſſumption of this ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme needeth ſome explanation. For the Lord would haue difference put betweene his owne commaundements and the lawes of men; and therefore we may not thinke, that he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all lawes of men ſimply to be obeyed: not ſimply, you muſt ſay then, but ſo farre forth as he requireth them to be obeyed.</p>
            <p>By which ſhort diſcourſe we learne, that thoſe additions by which I explaned the propoſition of the ſyllogiſme, were neceſſarie; and that the bond of conſcience is not the lawe of man, but of God: that we are bound to obey mans lawes not ſimply, but ſo farre forth as God requireth. And laſtly that this ſpeech, <hi>(All lawfull commaundements of Magiſtrates are neceſſarily to be obeyed)</hi> is true, not by the neceſſitie of the conſequent, as an axiome or principle which is manifeſt of it ſelfe; but by the neceſſitie of conſequence, as a concluſion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now that the lawes of men doe not binde the conſcience, it may further appeare by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, becauſe our freedome from the lawes iudiciall and ceremoniall, which in the Scriptures is extolled for ſo great a benefit, would be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then rather then a benefit, if wee ſhould in like manner be bound to the eccleſiaſticall and ciuill lawes of men. Againe, if they did binde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, there would be no difference betweene Gods lawes and mans lawes (in reſpect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177216:49"/> actions) and the one ſort would require ſimple obedience as well as the other, yea vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull commaundements would alſo binde the conſcience. But it is plaine, that ſimple obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is to bee performed onely to the lawes of God. To the lawes of men we are bound, not ſimply, but ſo farre forth as in obeying them, we alſo obey God, and no further; that is, as I ſaid, ſo farre as God commaundeth vs to obey them. Now, how farre forth God commaundeth vs to obey the lawes of men, will eaſily appeare by this diſtinction; for either they commaund ſuch things as God forbiddeth, and forbid ſuch things as he commaundeth, (which kinde of commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements are ſo farre from binding our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as that we are bound by the lawe of God to obey him in diſobeying them:) or they command ſuch things as God commaundeth, and forbid ſuch things as he forbiddeth, that by their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie the lawes of God may the better be obſerued, (to which kinde of commaundements wee are ſimply bound, becauſe as in obeying them we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God, ſo in breaking them we tranſgreſſe the lawe of God:) or laſtly, they commaund ſuch things as God hath not forbidden, and forbid ſuch things as God hath not commanded: to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this kind we are not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie bound, but ſo far forth as God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to obey them; that is, as <note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 16.</note> free (being not ſimplie bound to thoſe particulars, as neceſſarie in themſelues, but vſing them with free conſcience, as being indifferent, and therefore ſuch, as wherunto
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177216:49"/> our Chriſtian libertie extendeth,) and yet as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, thinking our ſelues ſo farre bound to obſerue them, <hi>as in neceſſarie for auoiding of Scandall and contempt,</hi> which God by his law hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Contempt: for it is neceſſarie, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 13. 5. 1. Pet. 2. 13. 16.</note> that wee ſhould ſubmit our ſelues to lawfull authoritie, not only for feare of puniſhment, but for conſcience ſake. For although wee bee free, as concerning the inner man; yet in reſpect of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, we muſt, as the ſeruants of God, ſubmit our ſelues to ſuch ſuperiours, as God hath ſet ouer vs, and not haue our libertie, as a cloake of naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe. Scandall alſo is to be auoided. Firſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſuperiour, that by our diſobedience we do not ſcandalize or offend him. Wherein our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hath giuen vs a notable example, who, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were (as hee <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 17. 25. 26. 27.</note> ſaith) free; yet was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to pay tribute money, for auoiding of offence. Secondly, in reſpect of the ſubiect; that he ſtumble not at the example of our diſobedience, being ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated thereby to doe the like. For whereas ſome thinke, that wee are not to obey the Magiſtrates commandement concerning a thing indifferent, if we imagine that ſome weake brother wil be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereat; they greatly miſtake the rule of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, who ſay theſe commandements are to bee obeyed for auoiding ſcandall, and not, that they are to be diſobeyed for auoiding of ſcandall. For if this were a ſufficient reaſon to excuſe our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we ſhould not need to obey almoſt any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of this kind, there being ſcarce any commaundement concerning things indifferent,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177216:50"/> wherewith we may not imagine ſome weake and ſcrupulous conſcience will bee offended. But wee muſt thinke our ſelues more bound, for auoiding of contempt and ſcandall, to obey a lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, then to diſobey, for auoiding a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed offence. That which we are to do in this caſe, is this: If we feare any will take offence, we muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to preuent it, by informing the partie, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath been ſaid. And hauing ſo done, we muſt do our owne dutie (whether he will be offended or not) in obeying the lawfull commandement of the Magiſtrate, ſo farre as it ſhall be neceſſarie for auoiding of ſcandall and contempt.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I haue entreated of the libertie of <note place="margin">§. 24. The libertie of Glorie.</note> grace, both that which is common to the faithfull in all ages; and alſo that which is peculiar to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians vnder the Goſpell. There remaineth (in a word to be ſpoken of) the libertie of glorie; which is not only a perfect deliuerance from ſin, miſerie, and al imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, (wherunto becauſe we are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 7. 24.</note> in this life, for here is as, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata, non perfect a libertas,</hi> we ought to aſpire towards this perfection) but alſo a fruition of happines and all the priuiledges of the citizens of heauen.</p>
            <p>This libertie is either of the ſoule alone, as at our death; when we may freely and with comfort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne our ſoules into the hands of God, that hee may commit the ſame to the <note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 16. 22.</note> bleſſed Angels to be tranſported into heauen, where wee are vnto the end of the world, comfortablie to expect our full redemption. Or it is of the bodie alſo at the day of iudgement (and is therefore called <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8. 23.</note> the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:177216:50"/> of our bodie) when it riſing vnto glorie, ſhall be freed from the ſeruitude <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note> of corruption, this <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 53. 54.</note> mortall putting on immortalitie, and this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible putting on incorruption; that death being ſwallowed vp in victorie, wee may enioy, both in our bodies and ſoules, the <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note> glorious libertie of Gods children in the kingdome of heauen. This ought we with earneſtnes of deſire <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 8. 22. 23</note> to aſpire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and with certainty of <note n="l" place="margin">Titus 2. 13. Luke 21. 28.</note> faith to expect; that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may bee wained from the world, hauing <note n="m" place="margin">Philip. 3. 20.</note> our conuerſation in heauen; and not either by the deſires of the world (which are but <note n="n" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. 2.</note> vanities) be allured and enſnared, or by the terrors thereof, (which are not <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> worthie the glorie that ſhall be reuealed), drawne into bondage.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you heard the doctrine of Chriſtian libertie. Now heare the vſe.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing this libertie is a benefit of ſo great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie <note place="margin">§. 25. The applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or vſe.</note> in it ſelfe, and of ſuch profit and neceſſitie to vs: Our firſt dutie is, to trie and examine our ſelues by that which hath been ſaid, whether wee haue as yet obtained this libertie, or not. If not, (as <note n="p" place="margin">John 8. 34.</note> 
               <hi>he which committeth ſinne, is the ſeruant of ſinne)</hi> we muſt labour to acknowledge and feele that miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruitude, wherein we are, vnder ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan (for he that is not free, and yet feeleth not his bondage, is drowned in ſinne, euen as he that is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer head and eares in the water, feeleth no weight thereof) that in the ſenſe of our miſerie, wee may not only truely and earneſtly deſire; but alſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vſe all meanes to attaine this libertie, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be at reſt, vntill we haue obtained it. It is ſtrange
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177216:51"/> to ſee what hard ſeruices men will vndergoe, and what great ſummes they wil forgo, to get an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly freedome; whiles this ſpiritual freedome, which is worth many worlds, will ſcarcely bee accepted, when men are called and inuited vnto it. Which ſheweth, that men naturally, are not only ſeruants, but willingly and wilfully continue in ſeruitude. But you will ſay, what meanes are we to vſe? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, 1. Diligently and conſcionablie to heare the Word, as being the meanes, which God hath ordained to call you to libertie. 2. To aske, ſeeke, knocke by earneſt and heartie prayer vnto God the author of this libertie, that hee would giue you the ſpirit of libertie. 3. To turne vnto God vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, laying hold vpon Chriſt by faith, and repenting of your ſins. <hi>Eris liber,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">August. in Joan. tract. 41.</note>, <hi>ſi fueris ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus, liber peccati, ſeruus iuſtitiae:</hi> You ſhal be free from ſin, if you will become the ſeruants of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. If God hath alreadie called vs vnto this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, our dutie is twofold, both which the Apoſtle mentioneth, Galath. 5. the one, <note n="*" place="margin">Galath. 5. 1.</note> that <hi>we ſtand faſt in this liberty, wherewith Chriſt Ieſus hath made vs free, and not ſuffer our ſelues to be entangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</hi> And the rather we muſt be carefull to ſtand faſt in this libertie, becauſe it is mightily aſſaulted by all the enemies of our ſaluation, the fleſh, the world, the diuell. Now, we are to ſtand ſtedfaſt, both in the doctrine of Chriſtian libertie, which is the doctrine of the Goſpell, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our ſelues to bee allured, or intoxicated, either with the golden <note n="r" place="margin">Apoc. 17. 4. 18. 3.</note> cup of the Babylonian ſtrumpet, the church of Rome, which doth not only bereaue
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:177216:51"/> men of Chriſtian libertie, but alſo draw them into Antichriſtian bondage: or with the Cyrcean cup of the Libertines, which transformeth Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme into Epicuriſme, and the libertie of the ſpirit into the libertie of the fleſh. And we are alſo to be ſtedfaſt and reſolute in the practiſe of Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie: as of vocation, not to be entangled againe with the ſeruitude of ſin and Satan, (for, if hauing profeſſed our ſelues freed thereof, we be againe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled therein, our latter end, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith <note n="s" place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 20. 21.</note>, will be worſe then our beginning). Of iuſtification, as not to ſubiect our ſelues to the lawes exaction of inherent and perfect righteouſnes to iuſtification, (for they which are <note n="t" place="margin">Galath. 3. 10.</note> of the workes of the law, are vnder the curſe) but without regard of our owne righteouſneſſe, to relie wholly for our iuſtification on the mercies of God, and merits of Chriſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by faith; and to hold him <note n="u" place="margin">Galath. 1. 8.</note> accurſed, though hee were an Angell from heauen, that ſhould teach otherwiſe. Of ſanctification, as not to ſubiect our ſelues to the dominion <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6. 12.</note> of ſinne, or to the terror or rigour of the law; but without ſeruile feare, willingly and cheerefully to ſerue our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, being well aſſured that he will couer our wants, and accept of our vnperfect endeuours. Of Chriſtian libertie in reſpect of outward things; as not to ſuffer our conſciences to be bound by the authoritie of any creature, inioyning them as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie in themſelues, and much leſſe to bind our owne conſciences, as ſcrupulouſly and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly putting religion either in the vſe or forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of them. Of the glorious libertie, as not to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:177216:52"/> ſuffer our ſelues by all the machinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, the fleſh, and the diuell, to be withdrawne from the hope and expectation of it; but comfortablie to liue as men <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8. 24.</note> ſaued in hope.</p>
            <p>The other dutie, is that which the Apoſtle men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth, Galath. 5. 13. <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſaith he, <note n="y" place="margin">Galath. 5. 13.</note> 
               <hi>you are called to libertie: only vſe not your libertie as an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the fleſh, but by charitie ſerue one another.</hi> That is, that we ſhould be carefull, both to auoid the abuſe <note place="margin">The abuſe of Christiam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</note> of Chriſtian libertie, and alſo to vſe it aright. The abuſe is manifold. As firſt, of the ſauing grace of God; when men do turne <note n="z" place="margin">Jud. 4.</note> it into wantonneſſe, their freedome from ſin, into a freedome to ſin, as though they were ſo freed from the law, as that they need not to obey it; as though good workes, becauſe they are not exacted to iuſtification, were in no reſpect needfull to ſaluation. <hi>We are not free,</hi> ſaith <hi>Luther</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">De libert. Christ.</note>, <hi>by faith in Chriſt from workes, but from the opinion of workes, that is, from the fooliſh preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iuſtification ſought by workes.</hi> Secondly, of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie, in reſpect of the creatures of God, and the vſe of things indifferent; when we do vſe them without regard of our dutie, to God, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or our ſelues.</p>
            <p>The dutie which wee owe to God, is pietie; to our neighbour in generall, charitie; and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to our ſuperiour, obedience and loyaltie; to our ſelues, ſobrietie. For theſe, as I ſaid, are the bounds of our libertie, which if we paſſe in the vſe thereof, we abuſe it. The vſe of our libertie is contrarie to pietie. Firſt, when we our ſelues are impious, and irreligious. For though the things in themſelues
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177216:52"/> be cleane, yet the vſe of them is vncleane to them that are impure. For as <note n="b" place="margin">Titus 1. 15.</note> to the pure, all things are pure, ſo to the vnclean nothing is cleane. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when the vſe of them is not ſanctified vnto vs, <note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 5.</note> either by the Word, as when we make more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things, then God in his word hath made, as drunkenneſſe, fornication, vſurie, &amp;c. or when we do not vſe them in faith and ſound perſwaſion out of the word of God, which is the charter of our libertie, that we may lawfully and with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience vſe them (for though nothing in it ſelfe bee vncleane, yet to him <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 14. 14. 23</note> that thinketh or doubteth that it is vncleane, it is ſo to him; for as the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of this particular, ſaith, <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne:)</hi> or by the duties of inuocation. As the vſe of meate and drinke, without either prayer to God for his bleſſing in the vſe, or thankſgiuing for the ſame. Thirdly, we abuſe our libertie irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, when we vſe it to the diſhonor of God, or to the hinderance of his worſhip and ſeruice, as in the immoderate and vnſeaſonable vſe of recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c. whereby men ſhew themſelues to be <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. Tim. 3. 4.</note> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of pleaſures more then of God.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe our vſe of the creatures, and of things indifferent, is againſt charitie, when wee vſe them without due regard of auoiding ſcandall and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Againſt loyaltie, when vſing our libertie with contempt of lawfull authoritie, wee make it a cloake to couer ſome naughtineſſe. And laſtly, againſt ſobrietie, when vnder pretence of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an libertie, the creatures of God, and other things indifferent, are vſed, either as inſtruments to ſerue,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177216:53"/> or as enſignes to diſplay, our pride or intemperate luſts, as in the exceſſe of meate and drinke, recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the vſe of the mariage bed, apparel, buildings and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>But let vs come to the right vſe of our Chriſtian <note place="margin">§. 26. The right vſe of Christian libertie.</note> libertie; which is twofold, either the ſanctification of our liues, or the pacification of our conſciences. As touching the former: the right vſe of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſauing grace is, when it is vſed to the free, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie, and cheerefull worſhippe and ſeruice of God, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, for <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 1. 74. 75.</note> that is the end of our libertie and redemption. The right vſe of Chriſtian liberty in outward things, is, when it is vſed to a free and cheerefull ſeruing, both one of <note n="g" place="margin">Galath. 5. 13.</note> another in charitie, and of the ſuperiour in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and loyaltie; that being free <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 19.</note> from all, we make our ſelues ſeruants vnto al, for their good. For as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, <note n="i" place="margin">De libert. Christ.</note> 
               <hi>A Chriſtian in reſpect of the inner man, is free, but in reſpect of the outward man hee is (through charitie) the ſeruant of all.</hi> And herein wee are to imitate the example of Chriſt; who, <note n="k" place="margin">Philip. 2. 5. 6.</note> though he were God, tooke vpon him the forme of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, to make vs free; and though he were the Lord of all, <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 20. 28.</note> came not to be miniſtred vnto, but to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And likewiſe of the bleſſed Angels; who, though they be glorious ſpirits, notwithſtanding take no ſcorne to be ſent forth into the <note n="m" place="margin">Hebr. 1. 14.</note> miniſterie and ſeruice for our good.</p>
            <p>The right vſe of the doctrine concerning the libertie of glorie, is, truly to beleeue it, and to liue as in expectation of it; knowing, that hee which hath this <note n="n" place="margin">1. Iohn. 3. 3.</note> hope, that he ſhall be like vnto Chriſt at
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177216:53"/> his appearance, will purifie himſelfe, as he is pure; that as he hopes to bee like him, in reſpect of the liberty of glorie, ſo he may in ſome meaſure reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his gratiouſnes, by the libertie of grace.</p>
            <p>But the chiefe vſe of this doctrine, is, to pacifie mens conſciences; without which (vnleſſe they ſleepe in carnall ſecuritie) they are ſo wonderfully perplexed, that neither can they liue in peace, nor attempt any thing almoſt with quiet minds. For whereas there be foure things which trouble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed conſciences, this doctrine is a ſoueraigne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to cleare and to appeaſe the conſcience, in reſpect of them all. The firſt, is the guilt of ſin, and feare of damnation. For when they conſcience is ſummoned before the iudgement ſeat of God, or terrified with the apprehenſion of his wrath, as in time of temptation, or affliction, or in the houre of death; when thou doeſt conſider the ſeueritie of Gods juſtice, who will not ſuffer ſinne to go vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, the rigour of the law, denouncing the curſe of God againſt euery euen the leaſt tranſgreſſion, the teſtimonie of thine owne conſcience, which is in ſtead of a thouſand witneſſes, accuſing and condemning thee of innumerable tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; how canſt thou thinke of appearing before God, who is greater then thy conſcience, to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified or condemned, without horror of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and confuſion of mind? But bleſſed be God, who hath granted vs this libertie of grace, that in the queſtion of iuſtification, wherby in this life we are freed from of damnation, and entituled vnto the kingdome of heauen, we need not looke
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:177216:54"/> into our owne obedience, or to the ſentence of the law; but may be aſſured, if we beleeue in Chriſt, that God doth iuſtifie vs, being ſinners in our ſelues, without reſpect of our workes; that he hath freed vs from the lawes exaction of inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, to the acceptation of our perſons; that he imputing the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer, accepteth of him as righteous in Chriſt; that the faithfull man hath libertie to appeale from the tribunall of iuſtice, to the throne of grace, from the ſentence of the law, to the promiſe of the Goſpell, and renouncing his owne righteouſnes, yea eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it as dung in the queſtion of iuſtification, to reſt alone in the mercies of God, and merits of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the world is ſo apt to abuſe this moſt comfortable doctrine, and to turne this gracious libertie into carnall licentiouſnes; it ſhall be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to adde this caution: That howſoeuer we are by our iuſtification in this life, entituled vnto the kingdome of heauen; and although by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and merits of Chriſt alone apprehended by faith, wee are both iuſtified and alſo ſaued: yet for as much as many deceiue themſelues with an idle conceit of faith, and with a vaine preſumption that they are iuſtified, when notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding <note n="p" place="margin">Prou. 30. 12.</note> they remaine in their ſins; therefore wee muſt thinke it moſt neceſſarie, being once iuſtified by faith, and entituled vnto the kingdome of heauen, to demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate our faith, and our iuſtification by a godly life; walking in that way of good workes, which God hath <note n="q" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 10.</note> prepared for vs to walke in towards our
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:177216:54"/> countrie in heauen. For though wee are iuſtified and ſaued by the merits of Chriſt alone apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by faith; notwithſtanding ſanctification is the <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 20. 32.</note> cognizance of them that are ſaued, and good workes are the euidence, according <note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 2. 6.</note> vnto which God will pronounce the ſentence of ſaluation. For as the <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 6. 44.</note> tree is knowne by his fruit; ſo he that <note n="u" place="margin">1. John 3. 7.</note> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth righteouſnes, is righteous, and in like manner by ſanctification our iuſtification is manifeſted. For true faith <note n="*" place="margin">Galath. 5. 6.</note> worketh by loue, and good workes are as the breathing of a liuely faith. And therefore though faith alone doth iuſtifie, as <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Galath. 2. 16. Rom. 3. 28.</note> teacheth, becauſe it alone doth apprehend the righteouſnes of Chriſt vnto iuſtification; yet as S. <hi>Iames</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Jam. 2. 14. &amp;c.</note> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that faith which is alone feuered from obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth not iuſtifie, neither alone, nor at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not a true faith. For euen as the bodie without breathing is knowne to be dead: <note n="z" place="margin">Jam. 2. 26.</note> ſo faith without workes is dead. We are therefore iuſtified in this life, and entituled vnto the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as to our inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, by faith without <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 4. 6.</note> works; but none are actually ſaued, nor inherit that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the life to come, but ſuch as firſt are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified. For as our Sauiour ſaith, we haue indeed not only remiſſion of ſins by faith, but alſo by faith we haue our inheritance; but yet, as he ſaith, <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 26. 18.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are ſanctified.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the conſcience of our manifold wants and imperfections, in thoſe duties which we do performe. For how can a man bee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that God, to <note n="c" place="margin">Job 15. 14. 15. 16.</note> whom no creature being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared is pure, will allow of his imperfect and ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:177216:55"/> obedience. And if he be not perſwaded, that his ſeruice is acceptable vnto God; with what hart can he performe it? The doctrine therefore of Chriſtian libertie aſſureth our conſciences, that we are freed from the lawes exaction of perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to the acceptation of our actions: that God couering our imperfections, as an indulgent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the perfect righteouſnes and obedience of Chriſt, imputeth not our wants vnto vs, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth of the truth of our will and deſire for the deed, and our ſincere endeuour for the perfect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. And therefore a Chriſtian may, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of this libertie, with comfort and cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes performe obedience, according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace receiued, being aſſured that our defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue and ſtained obedience, will be accepted of God through the mediation and interceſſion of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The third is the ſcruple of conſcience, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vſe of outward things, how far forth they may be vſed or forborne. For if a man be not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed herein, there wil be no end <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide Calu. Instit. lib. 3. cap. 19. §. 7.</note> of ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſitie and ſuperſtition. From this ſcruple alſo, the doctrine of Chriſtian libertie doth free vs: aſſuring vs, that to all theſe things our libertie doth extend, either to vſe them freely, or freely to forbeare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and that nothing is vncleane in it ſelfe, nor yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, if we be ſo perſwaded; and that to the cleane, all things are cleane. Prouided alwaies, that the vſe of this libertie bee kept within the bounds before mentioned, of pietie, charitie, loyaltie, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:177216:55"/>
            <p>The fourth and laſt is the horror of conſcience in the houre of death. For how can a man with comfort giue vp his ſoule to be ſeuered from the bodie, when he knoweth not, either what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his ſoule after the ſeparation thereof from the bodie, or how, and in what caſe his bodie ſhall riſe againe? But this doctrine doth aſſure vs, that Chriſt hath purchaſed, not only a libertie of grace in this life, but alſo of glorie for our ſoules againſt the end of our life, and for our bodies alſo, againſt the day of iudgement. So that we <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 10. 19. 20</note> haue libertie or boldnes, to enter into the holy places by the blood of Ieſus, by the new and liuing way, which he hath prepared for vs through the vaile, that is to ſay, his fleſh; being aſſured, that by reaſon of our vnion with Chriſt, we are riſen <note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 6.</note> againe with Chriſt, and with him ſet in the heauenly places, whither he is aſcended <note n="g" place="margin">Iohn 14. 2. 3. &amp; 17. 24. Philip. 3. 20. 21</note> to prepare a place for vs: and from whence hee will come againe to bring vs thither, that where he is, there we may be alſo. Wherefore in reſpect of this libertie, the faithfull may with comfort, both ſurrender our ſoules into the hands of God our mercifull Father, and alſo bequeath our bodies to the earth, in full aſſurance that our ſoules ſhall by the Angels bee tranſlated into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that our bodies ſhall at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, bee freed from the ſeruitude of corruption, and riſe againe to glorie: this mortall hauing put on immortalitie, and this corruptible incorruption, that it being againe reunited to the ſoule, wee may for euer and euer, enioy both in bodie and ſoule, the glorious libertie of the citizens of heauen.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177216:56"/> Vnto which libertie of glorie hee bring vs, who hath ſo dearely purchaſed it for vs, euen Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the righteous; to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be eternall praiſe and glorie, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 3. marg. lin. a fin. 3. reade <hi>c.</hi> 13. 30. &amp; <hi>c.</hi> 25. 33. p. 9. ad l. a fin. 9. write in the marg. §. 4. p. 10. l. 9. r. <hi>did iſſue.</hi> p. 33. marg. l. 21. r. <hi>Bellarm. tom.</hi> 3. p. 35. l. a fin. 3. r. <hi>one,</hi> ibid. r. <hi>happines. For</hi> p. 50. l. vlt. r. <hi>vntill.</hi> p. 67. marg. l. 3. r. <hi>corp.</hi> p. 78. l. a fin. 4. r. <hi>ſee men.</hi> p. 96. l. a fin. 2. r. <hi>pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: first,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
